<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Chaos: or, A discourse wherein is presented to the view of the magistrate, and all others who shall peruse the same, a frame of government by way of a republique, wherein is little or no danger of miscarriage, if prudently attempted, and thoroughly prosecuted by authority. Wherein is no difficulty in the practice, nor obscurity in the method; but all things plain and easie to the meanest capacity. Here's no hard or strange names, nor unknown titles (to amaze the hearers) used, and yet here's a full and absolute power derivative insensibly from the whole, and yet practically conveyed to the best men: wherein if any shall endeavour a breach, he shall break himself: and it must be so, that cats shall provide supper, here they shall do it suitable to the best palats, and easie to digest. By a well-willer to the publique weale.</title>
            <author>Well-willer to the publique weale.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 141 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 33 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A78571</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C1938</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E989_27</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R208259</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867223</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867223</idno>
            <idno type="VID">119528</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A78571)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 119528)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 147:E989[27])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Chaos: or, A discourse wherein is presented to the view of the magistrate, and all others who shall peruse the same, a frame of government by way of a republique, wherein is little or no danger of miscarriage, if prudently attempted, and thoroughly prosecuted by authority. Wherein is no difficulty in the practice, nor obscurity in the method; but all things plain and easie to the meanest capacity. Here's no hard or strange names, nor unknown titles (to amaze the hearers) used, and yet here's a full and absolute power derivative insensibly from the whole, and yet practically conveyed to the best men: wherein if any shall endeavour a breach, he shall break himself: and it must be so, that cats shall provide supper, here they shall do it suitable to the best palats, and easie to digest. By a well-willer to the publique weale.</title>
                  <author>Well-willer to the publique weale.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 54, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Livewel Chapman, at the Crown in Popes-head Alley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July 18".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:119528:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>CHAOS: OR, A DISCOURSE, WHEREIN Is preſented to the view of the Magiſtrate, and all others who ſhall peruſe the ſame, a Frame of Government by way of a Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blique, wherein is little or no danger of miſcarriage, if prudently attempted, and thoroughly proſecuted by Authority.</p>
            <p>Wherein is no difficulty in the Practice, nor obſcurity in the Method; But all things plain and eaſie to the meaneſt capacity.</p>
            <p>Here's no hard or ſtrange Names, nor unknown Titles (to amaze the hearers) uſed, and yet here's a full and abſolute Power deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vative inſenſibly from the whole, and yet practically conveyed to the beſt men: wherein if any ſhall endeavour a breach, he ſhall break himſelf: and if it muſt be ſo, that Cats ſhall provide Supper, here they ſhall do it ſuitable to the beſt Palats, and eaſie to digeſt.</p>
            <p>By a well-willer to the Publique Weale.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Livewel Chapman,</hi> at the Crown in <hi>Popes-head</hi> Alley. 1659.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="introductory_poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:119528:2"/>
            <lg>
               <l>THis Volume is not great nor large,</l>
               <l>Therefore 'tis bought with little charge:</l>
               <l>Here <hi>Cooks</hi> Reports and <hi>Bridgmans</hi> are</l>
               <l>Uſeleſs; our Laws are ſhorter far:</l>
               <l>Here we permit no long delays,</l>
               <l>Which alter Caſes ſundry waies:</l>
               <l>Here's <hi>Magna Charta</hi> full in view:</l>
               <l>Here every free-man hath his due:</l>
               <l>Here's no encouragement for knaves,</l>
               <l>Whom fitteſt 'tis to uſe as ſlaves.</l>
               <l>In this Diſcourſe here is ſupply</l>
               <l>For every ones neceſſity;</l>
               <l>Here dainties are for Palats fine,</l>
               <l>Here Gold and Pearl do both combine</l>
               <l>To beautifie the Diadem</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Europes</hi> darling, and the Queen</l>
               <l>Of Iſlands, <hi>Britain,</hi> which commands,</l>
               <l>A midſt the ſurging waves and ſands,</l>
               <l>Thoſe Nations, which if once made one,</l>
               <l>Will beautifie a glorious Throne,</l>
               <l>To entertain the mighty King</l>
               <l>T'w om Angels Haleluia's ſing.</l>
               <l>Which that we all endeavour may,</l>
               <l>With heart and voice let's truly pray.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:119528:2"/>
            <head>PREFACE. CHAOS</head>
            <p>SOme days ago taking into conſideration the lacerate and torn condition of her ruinous Fabrick, and casting about which way to provide for her ſelf, either to prevent the ſuddain fall thereof, or elſe to erect another Manſion ſuitable to her condition, purpoſing to reſerve ſo much of the old as is fit for neceſſary Offices, till better furniture may be had; hath in theſe few fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing pages attempted to put to view ſome things in order thereto, not doubting but good will come thereof. It's an unworn Path which ſhe hath troden, ſo that he that tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vels it, may perhaps meet with ſome ſeeming Rubs by the way; but there's no danger in any; the hardest ſtep may be troden without danger (which is only ſome trouble to the Roots in the firſt nine months of their work) but that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing paſt, ſhe brings her Paſſenger to quiet and pleaſant Manſions. If <hi>Aeneas</hi> and his followers had the confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence (<hi>Troy</hi> being turned to aſhes) to refuſe the pleaſures
<pb facs="tcp:119528:3"/>of the <hi>Carthaginian</hi> Court, and paſs <hi>Hercules</hi> Pillars (where they met with nothing but dangers) in hopes of a new Kingdom afterwards to ariſe, what ſhall we do, who though in ſome want of preſent Money, have all things accommodable to furniſh a well-being to our ſelves and our posterity, a rich and Potent People, more ready to obey, then the Magiſtrate to command, diſobeying no Edict promulged by Authority, offering hands and eſtates to carry on the work beyond all difficulties, for an unbiaſſed Republique? let not monitions be ſlighted, though proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from an unknown hand. Never any Law yet had its full force, whereof the Contriver was perfectly known: and though the weight of corrupt Laws commonly fall on the Contrivers heads; as he that made it treaſon to come armed into the Council, little thought he ſhould have been ſo caught first himſelf; neither dreamed <hi>Perillus,</hi> that his Bulls throat ſhould firſt bellow his own note; which may deter biaſſed men from ſelfiſh deſigns: yet here is nothing ſtrange, new, or unpracticable; nothing repugnant to the great Law given in the Mount, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſavouring of ſelf-reſpect, more then as a member of the Commonwealth, hoping (under the ſame, if it ſhall be put in practice) to Reap the fruits of what is here propounded, <hi>viz.</hi> peace, plenty, and the bleſſing of God. The Magiſtracy can never want money to do their work, if peace be preſerved: there's nothing more dangerous and deſtructive to our peace, then erecting of particular in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts, as our preſent Governours may well obſerve in their own School: how many have in their times ſince this Play begun, been eminently active upon the ſame ſtage, (where yet our preſent Governours are) who are all gone before the Play be half done? <hi>Chaos</hi> wiſhes the
<pb facs="tcp:119528:3"/>Tragical falls of thoſe by-past, who have miſcarried in the view of the preſent Actors, may ſhew them how to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent the like dangers hereafter: to which purpoſe ſhe hath aſſayed to ſhew, that a way may be found to a Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blique; yea, and ſuch a away, as if it be once put in pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, will not eaſily, nay can hardly be laid aſide; and ſo eaſie a way to be practiſed, as there's more facility by far in it, then in the rude and tumultuous ways we now are in: nothing we do ſavours of ſafety, or reliſhes like a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publique. In the way here propounded for elections, the meaneſt and rudeſt ſhall ſhew more gravity and reſpect to Magistracy, then the Magiſtrates themſelves (in the uſual tumultuary elections now in uſe) can do: here all things ſhall be done decently and in order, according to the Apoſtles advice in another caſe. But will ſome ſay, Here the vulgar ſhall have too great a liberty. That's anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, They can have no leſs, then to elect others fit to be elect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and whoever he is, though never ſo great, rich or po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, if he merit it not, there's no reaſon he ſhould Rule others with whom he hath nothing to do. If it be ſaid, The <hi>Agrarian</hi> hath here too much power: It's anſwered, <hi>Salus patriae ſuprema lex:</hi> the <hi>Agrarian</hi> pays the greateſt Aſſeſſes, therefore it's reaſon he have ſome hand in diſpoſing thereof. The Merchant cannot be ſo well confided in, who perceiving a ſtorm ariſe from any fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign quarter, or inbred commotion, can eaſily tranſport himſelf and his into the ſafety of another Prince or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publiques Harbour. The Trades-man hereby is capable of his due proportion, and each Corporation of his own Priviledge. No Lord ſuffers loſs, nor any diligent under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker diſcouraged: no Orphant unrelieved, nor any wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derer encouraged: and indeed, <hi>Chaos</hi> (as a publique Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent)
<pb facs="tcp:119528:4"/>endeavours here to propound nothing which ſhall more reliſh of ſelf, then to diſcover the ſelf-intereſts of the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſers or ſlighters of her propoſals. But ſhe is ſo confident in her aſſertions, as if any one ſhall undertake to queſtion any of them, ſhe doubts not but to make them more tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendently apparent and demonstrable to any ingenious capacity. It's true, here are many things left ſhort, which might be required to a perfect Platform of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which can only receive life and growth by time; yet as it is, ſhe ſaith, It's better then this we have, which has been ſo many ages in contriving; yea, and more pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cticable, with leſs charge and more profit. But next comes <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> with their imperious daughters the Suburbs, and they will bid high, ſaying, Shall we ſit in deſolation whilſt our glory is transferred into the Country? It may be ſuppoſed there's more ſafety and confidence in many well-governed and orderly ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, then in one imperious and domineering dame, who makes all the Cities in <hi>England</hi> like the late Queen-Mothers train marching up <hi>Holborn</hi> in Carts. It's too much to be lamented, that all our Nation is depopulated, our Cities laid waſt, our houſes uninhabited, and our riches all conſumed in vanity, (whilst the whole riches of the Country is here rifled away in riot:) were this City a provident Mother, ſhe would endeavour to promote the intereſts of her daughters, and rejoyce in their well-do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, being all their riches are for her ſupplies; inſomuch as if they be rich, ſhe cannot be poor; it's their plenty that furniſheth her ſtore, which the body of the City well knows, and will gain no ſmall wealth by the practice hereof. The Souldier may be ſuppoſed not to be pleaſed. But that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſuſpected; he ſhall enjoy far better terms then now
<pb facs="tcp:119528:4"/>he doth: when he ſhall be reſiant in his own Country, with his own enjoyments, he will profit more by half pay, then now (as an Itinerary and Mercenary man, lying conſtantly upon peny expences (and a ſtranger every where) he can do. But the Parliament (ſay ſome) will be moſt diſpleaſed, and never hereto agree, becauſe they are rich, and ſo in love with Command, as rather then they will loſe it, they will venter hard: having once adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured to grapple with a ſettled Monarch, they know their ſtrength, and it will (if they ſhall voluntarily ſhut them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves out) be too long before they ſhall come in again. But <hi>Chaos</hi> preſumes there's no one member in all the Houſe, who will own ſuch an aſſertion: beſides, they know very well they were never either appointed by God or man to be perpetual Lords, and all the Countrey (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides themſelves) their vaſſals: they may ſee upon what a tilt trip they were again ſet in the ſaddle; and now if they will endeavour to ſecure the reins, the best ſecurity they can uſe, is, by making the Weal Publick their chief deſign: for it's a thouſand to one whoſoever goes about to eſtabliſh his own Republique in the firſt place, ſhall be like him who having the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniency of travelling by Sea in a Man of War, every way furniſhed with the beſt Tackle and Furniture for all occaſions; ſhall ſlight that, and take himſelf to a lame Veſſel of his own making, where he has no other help, ſave his own hands, to prevent danger; in which (though he toil himſelf to death) he ſhall be overturned in the firſt storme, and periſhes alone, <hi>ſine ſolatio Amicorum,</hi> but, <hi>cum certo Riſu Inimicorum. Chaos</hi> is not for all this ſo confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent
<pb facs="tcp:119528:5"/>in her own Propoſals, as that ſhe thinks they cannot be mended: yet unleſſe ſome other will furniſh a better Frame, ſhe wiſhes this may be poliſhed, made fit for uſe, and put in practice; and ſo puts her ſelf to the pains to prepare meat for other Palats, cloathing for others backs, and houſes, ſafe manſions and harbours for others repoſe, in the enſuing Diſcourſe.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:119528:5"/>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The firſt days Work.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>ANte mare &amp; terras</hi>— as the wanton Poet ſings, <hi>rudis erat molis quem dixere Chaos.</hi> It might be well wiſhed the ſober heads of theſe times could uſe the Poers words, <hi>erat ante:</hi> but as if Fortunes Wheel were turned pſide down we may ſeem to be in the firſt condition of things again, <hi>ubi mollia pugnant duris.</hi> The Tail commands the Head, and all things are out of courſe; inſomuch as a <hi>Solon</hi> was never any where more needful. And the childrens burthens are grown ſo great, as if a <hi>Moſes</hi> appear not in time, it may be feared deliverance will come too late. After <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> knew that <hi>the most high bears rule,</hi> his Kingdom was reſtored. <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> no doubt wiſhes their Rulers had learned the ſame leſſon; and if they have, that the practice thereof may appear in publike: for though the Sword ſeems ſatiated with bloud, yet the Elements threaten Vengeance if we return not: And though for Rulers offences the People ſuffer, yet they ſeldom eſcape Scot-free. It were to be wiſhed, examples hereof were not ſo obvious in this Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration as they have been. Oh that <hi>Englands</hi> Rulers may ſee the work of the day! that Pride, Tyranny and Oppreſſion may receive their reward: which, whilſt men accuſed of greateſt crimes ſit as Judges in their own cauſe, cannot be expected; nor whilſt any of thoſe who have voices in making Laws, ſhall be admitted the Sanctuary of a Priſon, to ſhelter themſelves from the penalty there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:119528:6"/>of, can be hoped for. O <hi>horrenda &amp; impudica rabies!</hi> And that the People follow their Guides, is ſadly witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by this days Verdict of a <hi>Devonſhire</hi>-Jury at the Upper Bench Bar, who (in deſpight of the Judges honeſt, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable and wary Advertiſements) betrayed the Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent to the Fury of her over-potent Adverſary, and ſet the guilty free; whereby they have uſed their utmoſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours to proſtitute their maids, daughters and wives to the luſtful abuſion of the wicked at their wills.</p>
               <p>It were happy if every day ſpoke not the ſame or worſe language, ſo much reſembling that of <hi>Babel</hi> or <hi>Sodom,</hi> as nothing ever appeared ſo like the Poets old Chaos as this preſent Age. Theſe few particulars, amongſt the innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merary numbers of <hi>Babylons</hi> brats daily diſperſed to the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſion of all that hath any reſemblance of Goodneſs, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pels that hand which never intended any ſuch thing, to command the Preſs, which now hath liberty beyond mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, to meaſure even Immenſity it ſelf; not purpoſing to accuſe any for robbing the Publike, to erect a Private inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt; nor for pretended relieving the Publike, to ſtrain the ſtrings of their Inventions, to contrive new Impoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; nor yet for pretended Frugality to the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, to deſtroy thouſands of the Commons, by deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing juſtice, thereby cheriſhing all villany and wickedneſs in the higheſt meaſure.</p>
               <p>But when the Publike Faith of a Nation turns Bankrupt, who ſhall be accuſed? the Borrowers, or the Lenders? Sure if the Borrowers had not promiſed fair, the Lenders had not been. O unhappy hand, that ever drew Sword to countenance ſuch things, as the Paper bluſhes to bear the news of! Yet O happy age, that affordeſt Hands to effect what Heads cannot do! Yea, O happy people, who live in ſuch an Age where God commands the meaneſt of things to be means of Deliverance! Surely he hath Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies yet in ſtore for ſuch a people, if embraced: if not, let <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets declare the iſſue; or rather, the Saviour of the worlds weeping over <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:119528:6"/>to beware of what that rebellious City ſhortly after ſuffered.</p>
               <p>And if any ſhall ſay theſe Lines fell from <hi>Rabſhakeh's</hi> Pen; let them conſider, their origine, their birth and growth, is from <hi>Chaos.</hi> But the Poets word <hi>ante</hi> gives hopes, that as his <hi>ante</hi> was the fore-runner of better com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſures, where was <hi>mare, coelum &amp; terras;</hi> ſo this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent time elapſing, this Generation may hope to ſee <hi>mare &amp; terras</hi> in their proper places, and <hi>coelum ſupervolutans, illuminans, &amp; recreans.</hi> For never had Nation a Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracy better ſchooled and diſcipled, nor did ever Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate govern a people ſo generally capable of the beſt Rule of Government, as this is. But if, with <hi>Miles</hi> the Frier's man in the Fable, we flout and abuſe this coy Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs TIME, and improve not the advantage and oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity thereof, ſhe will be gone, and then repentance may come too late.</p>
               <p>Now that Chaos-like, out of which Order was produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, matter be adminiſtred for the framing of ſuch a ſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of Laws and Regiment, or at leaſt ſome Inſtruments brought to ſearch for ſome Foundation, or to diſcover ſome Quarries or other materials fit for ſo great a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brick, which is not to be expected to be done all at once, and all in one day, by any one private hand, nor yet from all the heads of our Governours at preſent, whoſe cares for ſpeedy remedy to prevent imminent dangers, takes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way much of their time from theſe other contrivances. And though no one piece of what ſhall here be offered, ſhall be found fit ſtuff to build withal, yet may other more dextrous Artiſts be hereby invited to furniſh the proper materials for the very work it ſelf.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chaos</hi> never travelled; or if ſhe did, it was when ſhe was in the womb of Nothing. So ſhe brings no cuſtomes from other Countries, nor Laws from other Lands: one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as the birth is produced in its proper dimenſions, not reſpecting any other feature or proportion in the whole frame of Nature, who leſt any part or member thereof
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:119528:7"/>ſhould ſteal anothers right, hath framed all creatures, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimate, and Inanimate (if ſuch a conjecture may be ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined) in a convenient diſparity each to other: yet ſo, as there is ſtill an harmonious parity in the whole. So <hi>Chaos</hi> neither doats upon her neighbour-cuſtoms more then is convenable, nor is ſhe affected with ſtrange novelties fetcht from far Countries, ſo ardently as to ſurfeit there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: ſhe is neither bewitched with the beauty and riches of the Grand Seignior's <hi>Seraglio,</hi> neither is ſhe enamour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the Cantonian formalities. All the Mitres in the Conclave of <hi>Rome,</hi> cannot invite her to fetch her Laws from <hi>Italy,</hi> nor all the Decencie and Liberty of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> furniſh her with more then ſome miſs-ſhapen pieces, which ſhe purpoſes to poliſh for her own purpoſe. She purpoſes not to pry too deep into the Spaniards Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burnt Inquiſition, nor yet to roave too far in the frigid Zone of the Tartarian Territories; but out of her own ſtore, <hi>Chaos</hi>-like, is her furniture; only the deck and dreſs may ſeem to be ſometimes borrowed from one, ſometimes from another. Yet unleſs ſhe be new built, ſo as to ſuit with the temper of her own climate, ſhe will be unſervice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, and her fruit abortive.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chaos</hi> conſidering that in ſix days a Creation of excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent beauty and proportion, ſuiting to the magnitude thereof, in number, weight and meaſure, was by an all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powerful hand produced, has propounded to her ſelf ſix days work for perfecting of her intended Creation. (<hi>Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> ſhe calls it, becauſe ſhe finding all the Rafters of her old Building rotten, and the Mortices and Tenons full of rubbiſh, all the Pins either broken or pull'd from their places, all the Beams battered and bruiſed, and indeed the whole Fabrick ready to fall about her ears.) As Light was the firſt thing in the Creation, and ſo properly called the work of the firſt day; ſo for her firſt days work ſhe propounds for the Balancing of Intereſts, and reducing each piece to its proper place, (the <hi>praecognita</hi> being firſt allowed of, <hi>viz.</hi> a time prefixed (as already in great wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:119528:7"/>the preſent Rulers have done) for the Parliaments ſitting; within which time if they be idle, their work will be left undone; and what will be their Reward, if ſo?) So as if any one piece ſeem to be wreſted out of its place, the weight and frame of the whole prevents it.</p>
               <p>It is proponed, that one Common Intereſt be erected, whereof each member ſhall ſhare, as well in receiving protection from, as giving contribution to; and to be ſo incorporated, as no variant opinion, either in Religion or Policie, ſhall be able to weaken the whole: (but if any ſhall endeavour it, it ſhall by weakning and deſtroying it ſelf, add ſtill to the whole.)</p>
               <p>And as a light to the enſuing Intendment, <hi>Chaos</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounds, That in this Iſland of <hi>Great Britain</hi> (heretofore conſiſting of many, but of late days of three diſtinct Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipalities; heretofore divided into many, but now either all ſpeaking, or all underſtanding one and the ſame lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, and alſo incorporated into one Commonwealth) be one Law, and one Regiſtery, diſperſed into ſeverall parts thereof; and ſo diſpoſed, as each part ſhall be ſubſervient to other, and each communicative to other, and all to the whole; not purpoſing to deprive the Head of his due reſpect, neither the Body, or any member thereof, of their proper dues, according to each ones particular propriety and proportion, without deſtruction or diminution of any Right, Franchiſe or Priviledge due to any Lord of Mannor, or other Proprietor whatſoever, or detraction from the juſt freedom of any Engliſh-men: wherein is propoſed to the Magiſtrate, Honour and reſpect; to the Lawyer, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit; to the People, enjoyment of <hi>Magna Charta;</hi> and to the Republick, the enjoyment of all. The diſtribution whereof, <hi>Chaos</hi> propounds to be, National, Provincial, Sub-Provincial, and Parochial; each Regiſtry to have his Court and Officers. To which Courts and Regiſteries all matters of Civil concernment ſhall be reduced: and this to be erected within eight months, ſo that the preſent Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtracie
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:119528:8"/>may have the honour to lay the foundation there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and to reap the benefit alſo, when others ſhall come in their places, to eaſe their ſhoulders of the burthen of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, which none or few in the Nation are or can be enabled to go thorow ſo dexterouſly as they now are, who are at preſent entruſted therewith. In the intervall of which time, <hi>Chaos</hi> propounds (as that light may appear to be the fruit of this firſt days work) that all Suits in Law or Equity may be determined within ſix Months; and to that end, that ſufficient time be alotted to the Judges Iti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerant in the ſeveral Circuits, for hearing and determining of all matters which ſhall be brought before them: and that within one month after the Circuit, another Term be kept in <hi>Westminſter,</hi> where all further Iſſues may be joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; and another Circuit a month after that, for finiſhing the whole buſineſs as to matter of Law.</p>
               <p>And for all Actions depending in Equity, let Judges in Chancery ſit <hi>de die in diem,</hi> and cauſe ſpeedy examinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of all things needfull to be made, and bring all to hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in <hi>Michaelmas</hi> Term next, or ſhortly after, upon pain of great Fines to be impoſed upon the Judg or Judges who ſhall be remiſs herein, and abſolute loſs of the Cauſe to the Clyent, whether Plaintiff or Defendant, that ſhall endeavour further delayes; and let Judges enow be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for that purpoſe at the Commonwealths charge. The like courſe to be uſed by all Committees: and that no new Suits be in the Interim commenced, That publike notice hereof be given to the whole Nation, at or before the next Aſſizes; and this to ſuffice for the firſt dayes work: only to ſhew what's intended for further light to the whole Creation, which is to receive Life and Perfection in the following days, within the time allotted, is promiſed Rules for the five dayes work to come, <hi>viz.</hi> For the</p>
               <p n="2">2. Rules for Regiſters, which ſhall but be one to all purpoſes, but diſtributed into its ſeveral parts.</p>
               <p n="3">3. For the Law and Juriſdiction of each ſeveral Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſterial Court.</p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:119528:8"/>
               <p n="4">4. For future Elections and Tranſactions of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p n="5">5. For Aſſeſments, Cuſtoms, Exciſe, and Proviſion for the Poor. And</p>
               <p n="6">6. For Trade and Husbandry; under which the Militia ſhall be comprehended, as alſo Proviſion made for the Miniſtry and Schools of Learning, as the perfection of the work: upon each of which, if this be approved of by Authority, and a <hi>Fiat</hi> put to the firſt dayes work already propoſed, a ſeveral Diſcourſe is intended for each ſuccee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding dayes work, in their proper times.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The Second Days Work.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The firſt days work to view hath brought</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The Laws in Nature</hi> Chaos <hi>taught:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The ſecond days ſeparation make</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Old ſenceleſs</hi> Chaos <hi>fabrick quake.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p n="1">1. LEt a National Regiſtery be appointed at <hi>Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">National Regiſter.</note> to conſiſt of a Regiſter and ſix Clerks aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant or deputies, each of which to have ſo many writing and examining Clerks under them as the work ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire; which may be encreaſed at pleaſure for diſpatch, and diſcharged again, when the croud of buſineſs ſhall be over: let certain Rules be given, and competent Fees allowed.</p>
               <p n="2">2.
<note place="margin">Provinces.</note> Let each County in <hi>England</hi> be one entire Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince, and thoſe again allotted to the juriſdiction of the ſaid ſeveral ſix Clerks or Deputies, <hi>viz.</hi> ſo many Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, Towns and Cities, as are comprized within the riding of every reſpective Circuit of the Judges, and no more,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:119528:9"/>to be within the Cognizance or Regiſtry of one Clerk, Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtant or Deputy; and ſo the ſix ſeveral Circuits to be reſpectively apportioned to the ſix Clerks, (that is to ſay) to each Clerk one Circuit; with whom entries to be made of all particular Eſtates lying in ſeveral Counties in the ſame Circuit.</p>
               <p n="3">3.
<note place="margin">Provincial Register.</note> In each Shire-Town, within each ſeveral and reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive Province, let a Provincial Regiſter be appointed; each Provincial Regiſter to have two Clerks, Aſſiſtants or Deputies; between whom each County or Province ſhall be equally divided, half the Sub-provinces, Hundreds, Wapentakes to one, the other half to the other, ſave the County and Province of <hi>York;</hi> and there to be three Clerks, Aſſiſtants or Deputies, <hi>viz.</hi> for each riding one; each Aſſiſtant or Deputy to have ſo many writing Clerks and Examiners under every of them apart, as the work ſhall require.</p>
               <p n="4">4.
<note place="margin">Sub-Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincial Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſter.</note> Each ſeveral Wapentake, Hundred, Lath or Rape, to have a particular Regiſter, by the name of Sub provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Regiſter; and be reputed a Sub-province, to have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendance on, and reſpect to the Provincial Regiſter, within whoſe Province or County the ſame is, and not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therways (ſave as hereafter is directed) each Sub-provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Regiſter to have one Clerk, Aſſiſtant or Deputy, and ſo many writing and examining Clerks under him again as the work ſhall require.</p>
               <p n="5">5.
<note place="margin">Pariſh Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſter.</note> Each ſeveral Pariſh ſhall be one Regiſtry, and have a diſtinct Regiſter; and where the Pariſhes ſhall be too lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, let two or more be joyned together into one Pariſh, and have one Parochial Regiſter; each ſeveral and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective Parochial Regiſter to have under him a Clerk, Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtant or Deputy, and under-Clerks alſo as need ſhall require.</p>
               <p n="6">6.
<note place="margin">Entries with the ſix Clerks.</note> All and every perſon and perſons, bodies Politique and Corporate, who ſhall have any Eſtates in two or more ſeveral Circuits, ſhall enter the ſame diſtinctly with the ſeveral and reſpective Clerks; that is to ſay, with every
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:119528:9"/>Clerk or Deputy in the National Regiſtry reſpectively, ſo much as lies within his Circuit or Clerkſhip, and no more; and when the entries of the whole ſhall be perfected, the total of the Annual values in each reſpective Circuit, ſhall be tranſmitted from every ſeveral Clerk, with whom en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try of any parcel of ſuch Eſtate ſhall be made, to that Clerk with whom the Entry of the largeſt proportion of ſuch Eſtate ſhall lie; or where the chief reſidence, or moſt ancient ſeat or title of Honour to the preſent Ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners thereof, is or ſhall be.</p>
               <p n="7">7. All and every perſon and perſons,
<note place="margin">Entries in the National Registry.</note> bodies Politique and Corporate, who have or claim any Right, Title or Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, either in Poſſeſſion or Reverſion to any Mannor of Inheritance of the annual or yearly value of 1000 <hi>li.</hi> or upwards; and alſo ſuch who have Eſtates of Inheritance in ſeveral Counties or Provinces, though of leſs value, ſhall enter the ſame in the National Regiſtry, with the proper Clerk or Clerks, according to former direction, and not elſewhere.</p>
               <p n="8">8. All perſon and perſons,
<note place="margin">Provincial Entries.</note> bodies Politique and Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porate, who ſhall have, or claim to have any Right, Title or Intereſt, either in Poſſeſſion or Reverſion, to any Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of Inheritance within any one Province, above the yearly value of 100 <hi>li.</hi> and not exceeding 1000 <hi>li. per an.</hi> and ſhall have no Eſtate elſewhere, ſhall enter the ſame in the Provincial Regiſtry within which it lies (that is to ſay) with each reſpective Clerk, Aſſiſtant or Deputy, ſuch part thereof as ſhall lie within the limits of his part of the Regiſtry, for the County, Shire or Province, and not elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where; and (when the Entries thereof ſhall be perfected) Returns ſhall be made by the other Clerk or Clerks, Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtant, Deputy or Deputies (where the meaner or leſſer part or parts of the ſame ſhall lie, to the Clerk, Aſſiſtant or Deputy, with whom Entry ſhall be made of the Manſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Houſe, ancient ſeat, or chief Inheritance) of the whole yearly value or values, with him or them entred; which ſhall be added to the other Entry, remaining with that
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:119528:10"/>Clerk or Deputy, by whom the chief Entry ſhall be made as aforeſaid.</p>
               <p n="9">9.
<note place="margin">Entries Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provincial.</note> All ſuch perſon and perſons having Eſtates as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, above the clear yearly value of 10 <hi>li.</hi> and not exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing 100 <hi>li. per annum,</hi> lying within any one Hundred, Wapentake, Lath; Rape or Province, and ſhall have no Eſtate elſewhere, ſhall enter the ſame with the Sub-pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincial Regiſter within whoſe Regiſtry the ſame lies, and not elſewhere.</p>
               <p n="10">10.
<note place="margin">Parochial Entries.</note> And all ſuch perſon or perſons having Eſtates as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid, in any one Pariſh or Parochial Regiſtry not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding 10 <hi>li. per annum,</hi> and ſhall have no Eſtate of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance elſewhere, ſhall enter the ſame with the Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of that Pariſh where it lies, and not elſewhere; and alſo all Inhabitants, Tenants, Owners and Occupants of all Lands, Tenements and Hereditaments, ſhall enter the ſame with the Parochial Regiſter where the ſame lie, and under what Title, Condition, Rent or Service the ſame are held, and of whom, and to whom the ſaid Rents or ſervices are payable.</p>
               <p n="11">11.
<note place="margin">Entries of Debts.</note> In like manner Entries ſhall be made of all Debts and Specialties exceeding 1000 <hi>li.</hi> with the National Regiſter; of all Debts above 100 <hi>li.</hi> and not exceeding 1000 <hi>li.</hi> with the Provincial Regiſter; of all Debts above 10 <hi>li.</hi> and not exceeding 100 <hi>li.</hi> with the Sub-provincial Regiſter; and of all other ſmaller Debts not exceeding 10 <hi>li.</hi> with the Parochial Regiſter, where the party and parties indebted ſhall ſeverally and reſpectively live, or the Eſtate lie whereon the ſame ſhall be charged: each ſuch reſpective Entry to be made with that Clerk Aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, Deputy, Inferiour Regiſter, or his Deputy, within whoſe reſpective limits the party indebted ſhall then live, or the Eſtate therewith charged lie; according to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection for Entries as aboveſaid.</p>
               <p n="12">12.
<note place="margin">National Regiſters Certificate.</note> After all ſuch Entries ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e made and perfected as aforeſaid, the National Regiſter ſhall (within 14. daies) certifie the name, nature, and value of every ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:119528:10"/>and reſpective Eſtate with him entred, and by whom the ſame is claimed, and by what Title, and in whoſe tenure or occupation the ſame is, to the ſeveral and reſpective Provincial Regiſters within whoſe limits the ſame ſhall lie; that is to ſay, To each Provincial Regiſter ſo much as lies within his Province or Regiſtry, and no more.</p>
               <p n="13">13.
<note place="margin">Provincial Certificate.</note> Each ſeveral Provincial Regiſter ſhall within eight daies after receipt of ſuch Certificate as aforeſaid from the National Regiſter, make the like Certificate to each Sub-provincial Regiſter within his juriſdiction, of the name, nature and value of every ſeveral and reſpective E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate with him entred, or to him certified; and by whom the ſame is claimed, and by what Title, and in whoſe oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupation the ſame is; that is to lay, To each ſeveral and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective Sub-provincial Regiſter of ſo much as lies within his Sub-province, and no more.</p>
               <p n="14">14.
<note place="margin">Sub-provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Certifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate.</note> Each ſeveral Sub-provincial Regiſter ſhall within ſix daies after receipt of ſuch Certificate as aforeſaid, from his Provincial Regiſter, make the like Certificate to each Parochial Regiſter within his juriſdiction, of the name, nature and value of every ſeveral and reſpective Eſtate with him entred, or to him certified; and by whom and by what Title the ſame is claimed, and in whoſe occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation the ſame is; that is to ſay, To each diſtinct Paro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chial Regiſter of ſo much as lies within his Pariſh onely, and no more.</p>
               <p n="15">15.
<note place="margin">Double claims to be certified.</note> Each ſeveral and reſpective Parochial Regiſter (forthwith upon receipt of the ſeveral Certificates afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid) ſhall examine all the Entries made in his reſpective Regiſtry; and where ſeveral claims ſhall be made by ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral perſons, under ſeveral Titles to one and the ſame thing, the Regiſter ſhall give notice thereof to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Inhabitants, Tenants or Occupiers thereof, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to his Sub-provincial Regiſter, within ſix days; and if it exceed the Cognizance of the Sub-provincial Regiſter, he ſhall certifie the ſame to the Provincial Regiſter, who if it exceed his Cognizance, ſhall certifie the ſame to the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:119528:11"/>National Regiſter; each to certifie to other within ſix days after the date of the Certificate to him directed.</p>
               <p n="16">16.
<note place="margin">Parochial Regiſters Certificate.</note> Each Parochial Regiſter ſhall likewiſe certifie to the Sub-provincial Regiſter under whoſe juriſdion he is, the names and values of all Eſtates of Inheritance lying with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the ſame Pariſh, and of all Fee-farme-rents, Quit-rents, Rents of Aſſize, Copyhold-rents, or other dry-rents what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, iſſuing out of the ſame Pariſh; alſo the names, qualities and habitations of the ſeveral and reſpective Owners and Proprietors thereof, whether reſiant in the ſame Pariſh, or elſewhere, within ten days after the firſt Entries thereof in his Parochial Regiſtry ſhall be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected. And alſo the total Annual value of all Eſtates of Inheritance within his Pariſh or Regiſtry, in one entire ſum at the foot thereof.</p>
               <p n="17">17.
<note place="margin">Sub-pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince Certi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficates.</note> Each Sub-provincial Regiſter ſhall likewiſe certi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie to his Provincial Regiſter within whoſe juriſdiction he ſhall reſpectively be, the ſeveral and reſpective names and values of all Eſtates lying and being in his Sub-pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince; and the names, qualities and habitations of all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons whatſoever Owners thereof; and alſo the whole clear yearly value of all ſuch, caſt up in one ſum at the foot thereof, within ten days after his receipt of all the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Parochial Certificates aforeſaid, within his Sub-pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince.</p>
               <p n="18">18.
<note place="margin">Province Certificate.</note> Each Provincial Regiſter ſhall likewiſe certifie to the National Regiſter (within twenty daies after his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt of all the ſeveral Certificates from the ſeveral Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſters within his Province) the names, qualities and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitations of all perſon and perſons whatſoever not reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in his Province, who claim any Eſtate in the ſame Province; and the whole yearly values of all Eſtates, ſo by them reſpectively claimed, and alſo the whole and clear yearly value of the whole Province, in one entire ſum by its ſelf.</p>
               <p n="19">19.
<note place="margin">Three years Certificates.</note> The like Certificates ſhall be made and renewed every three years by ſeveral Regiſters aforeſaid, as follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth:
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:119528:11"/>each Parochial Regiſter ſhall on or before the 10. day of <hi>January</hi> triennially certifie to the Sub-provincial, and each Sub-provincial on or before the 30. of the ſame Month, and the Provincial to the National on or before the 20. of <hi>February</hi> in the ſame year, upon penalty of the forfeiture of 20 <hi>li.</hi> by each reſpective Parochial Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, 40 <hi>li.</hi> by each Sub-provincial Regiſter, and 100 <hi>li.</hi> by each Provincial Regiſter, to the uſe of the Republique, to be levied by order of the next Superintendent Regiſterial Court; and alſo removal from their ſeveral Regiſterial places of all Regiſters, Clerks or Deputies, who ſhall neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect the ſame.</p>
               <p n="20">20.
<note place="margin">Entries within ſix Months.</note> The firſt Entries to be made and perfected in all and every the reſpective Regiſtries aforeſaid, by the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Owners, Occupants, Proprietors and Claimants a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid, within ſix Months after erection of the Regiſtry aforeſaid; and the Certificates to be all made and retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and entries perfected thereof, by every ſeveral and reſpective Regiſter, within two Months after the end of the ſaid ſix Months, upon penalties to the Regiſters as aforeſaid, and upon double the penalty (to each ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral and reſpective Clerk, Aſſiſtant or Deputy, who ſhall neglect the ſame) to what is impoſed on any Provincial Regiſters, and upon penalty of 500 <hi>li.</hi> to the National Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſter himſelf.</p>
               <p n="21">21.
<note place="margin">National Regiſters Seal.</note> The Seal of the Nation Regiſtry ſhall be the great Seal of <hi>England;</hi> and the National Regiſter and his ſix Aſſiſtants, to be the Keepers thereof: the ſame not to be made uſe of to any purpoſe whatſoever, ſave in preſence of the National Regiſter and two Aſſiſtants for the time being.</p>
               <p n="22">22. Each ſeveral Province ſhall have a peculiar Seal,
<note place="margin">Provincal Seals,</note> whereupon ſhall be the Arms or Cognizance of the ſame Province, City or Corporation, where the Regiſtry for that Province ſhall be kept; and the name of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince engraven in plain legible Engliſh letters about the ſame; and ſhall be in the cuſtody of the Regiſter and his
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:119528:12"/>Aſſiſtants of each ſeveral and reſpective Province; not to be uſed in any caſe whatſoever, ſave in preſence of the Regiſter, and one Aſſiſtant or Deputy of the ſame Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry.</p>
               <p n="23">23.
<note place="margin">Sub-provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Seals.</note> Each Sub-provincial Regiſtry ſhall have a particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Seal, with the Arms or Cognizance of the Regiſter for the time being; and alſo the name of the Sub-province and Province, for which it ſhall be uſed, engraven in plain legible characters about the ſame; to be in the keeping of the Regiſter and his Clerk, Aſſiſtant or Deputy; and not to be uſed in any caſe, where they ſhall not be both of them perſonally preſent.</p>
               <p n="24">24.
<note place="margin">Parochial Seals.</note> Each ſeveral Pariſh ſhall have a particular Regiſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial Seal: whereupon ſhall be engraven in plain legible Engliſh letters, the name of the Pariſh, Sub-province, and Province, for which the ſame ſhall be uſed; and alſo in the middle thereof, the name and ſirname of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſter, without any other Cognizance or Coat of Arms: to be in the cuſtody of the Regiſter, Miniſter and Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardens of the ſame Pariſh for the time being; and not to be uſed but in preſence of the Regiſter and Miniſter (or one of the Church-wardens then in being, with the Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter) in the Miniſters abſence.</p>
               <p n="25">25.
<note place="margin">Entries cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified.</note> After the perfecting of all Entries and Certificates as aforeſaid, the ſeveral Regiſters in the whole Nation (each in their ſeveral and reſpective limits and juriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) ſhall give Certificates to all Owners and Proprietors of all Eſtates whereto no double claims ſhall be made, and affix the Regiſterial Seal of the particular Regiſtry thereto, (when and to whom they ſhall be deſired:) and where ſeveral Eſtates to the ſame thing ſhall be claimed, entred, and certified as aforeſaid, as the preſent Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion to one or more, the reverſion or remainder to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or others, a Joynture or Dower, Leaſe or any other legal title and warrantable claim, to any other perſon or perſons, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> whatſoever; the ſame ſeveral titles ſhall be ſeverally certified to the ſeveral Claimants and Proprie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:119528:12"/>thereof, and the Seal affixed to the ſame ſeveral Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificates: which ſhall be a good and warrantable Eſtate, to whom the ſame ſhall be given as aforeſaid, againſt all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther claimants whatſoever.</p>
               <p n="26">26.
<note place="margin">Manner of Certificates.</note> In giving out the ſeveral Certificates by the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Regiſters under their reſpective Regiſterial Seals, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect ſhall be had to the ſeveral values of the reſpective Eſtates to be by them certified, and to the Situtation thereof: For no Parochial Regiſters Seal ſhall be put to any Certificate exceeding the value of 10 <hi>li.</hi> by the year, all lying within his Parochial Regiſtry; no Sub-provincial ſhall put his Seal to any Certificate exceeding 100 <hi>li. per annum,</hi> lying within his own limits; neither any Provincial Seal ſhall be put to any Eſtate exceeding the yearly value of 1000 <hi>li.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="27">27. All perſon &amp; perſons, bodies Politique &amp; Corporate,
<note place="margin">Entries not made with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in 6. months void.</note> having or claiming any Eſtate, Right, Title or Intereſt, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Poſſeſſion, Reverſion, either by Leaſe, Joynture or Mortgage, not entring their claims thereto, within the times aforeſaid, with the ſeveral Regiſters with whom they ſhall reſpectively lie; and not taking the reſpective Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſters Seal for warranty thereof, within three Months af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Entry thereof as aforeſaid, (unleſs in caſe of Infan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, or being beyond the Seas, or where the party who en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred the ſame ſhall die before the perfecting thereof,) ſhall be for ever after debarred from making any claim to the ſame, or any part thereof.</p>
               <p n="28">28.
<note place="margin">Manner of entring Debts.</note> Entries ſhall be made within three Months after the ſetling of the Regiſtry, of all manner of Debts, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther upon Specialty or not, <hi>viz.</hi> of all Debts exceeding 1000 <hi>li.</hi> in the National Regiſtry; of all above 100 <hi>li.</hi> and not exceeding 1000 <hi>li.</hi> in the reſpective Provincial Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, where the Debtor or Debtors ſhall live, or the Eſtate or Eſtates ſhall lie, whereon the ſame ſhall be reſpectively charged; of all the Debts above 10 <hi>li.</hi> and not exceeding 100 <hi>li.</hi> in the reſpective Sub-provincial Regiſtry, where the Debtor lives, or the Eſtate lies charged therewith; and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:119528:13"/>of all ſmall Debts not exceeding 10 <hi>li.</hi> principal, in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective Parochial Regiſtry where the parties live who ſhall owe the ſame, or the Eſtate lies whereon the ſame ſhall be charged. In all Entries of Debts aforeſaid, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect is to be had to the principal, for the ſeveral Entries to be made as aforeſaid; as, if 10 <hi>li.</hi> have been owing two years, whereby ſo much intereſt ſhall be due therefore, the ſame ſhall notwithſtanding that be entered in the Paro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chial Regiſtry; and ſo of other.</p>
               <p n="29">29.
<note place="margin">Certificates of Debts.</note> Upon the Debtors acknowledging any Debt to any Regiſter wherewith the ſame ſhall be ſo entred, the reſpective and ſeveral Regiſters ſhall give a Certificate thereof to the Creditor or Creditors deſiring the ſame, under the Seal of their reſpective Regiſtries; which ſhall be ſufficient warranty for recovery thereof, when the ſame ſhall become due, without any farther trouble to the Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditor then a claim to be made thereof, to be entred with the Regiſter any time after the time ſhall be elapſed, when the ſame ſhould have been paid.</p>
               <p n="30">30.
<note place="margin">Entries of Bargains and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracts.</note> All manner of Bargains and Contracts, whereby any Eſtate of Inheritance, Mortgage or Leaſe ſhall be made, or any Right transferred from one hand to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and where any Debt ſhall be contracted by any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or perſons to any others whatſoever, and all Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, Conditions, Conſiderations, and times of pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in preſence of the ſeveral parties between whom the ſeveral Contracts ſhall be made; and thereupon the reſpective Regiſters (with whom every or any ſuch En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries ſhall be made and acknowledged) ſhall give Certifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates to the ſeveral parties deſiring the ſame, of ſo much as concerns the party to whom it is given, under the Seal of the reſpective Regiſtries, and copies thereof to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther parties deſiring the ſame, under their hands only; that is to ſay, He to whom moneys is to be paid, ſhall have the Seal for the mony; and he who is to have the thing bargained for, the ſeal therefore, and the counter-parts to the other party under the Regiſters hand: And Entries
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:119528:13"/>of all payments and diſcharges of bargains ſhall be made.</p>
               <p n="31">31. In all Entries of any Bargains,
<note place="margin">The manner of entring bargains.</note> the parties ſhall perſonally acknowledge the ſame to the Regiſter, in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of two known perſons inhabiting within the Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, who ſhall atteſt their knowledge of the perſons atteſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Bargain, and to be the ſame perſons whoſe names ſhall be then entred upon oath; and not otherways, ſave where both the perſons bargaining ſhall be ſufficiently known to the Regiſter or his Deputy, to be the ſame per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons they ſpeak themſelves to be.</p>
               <p n="32">32. In all Entries, the name, ſirname, quality,
<note place="margin">Method of Entries.</note> and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation of every perſon and perſons ſhall be entred; and alſo the name, ſituation, content, and value of all Eſtates, the day and year of the entry, with all other conditions, Covenants, and agreements, and conditions requiſite, and all other circumſtances requiſite for declaration of the whole truth, in as few words as may explain the ſame.</p>
               <p n="33">33.
<note place="margin">Infants and Travellers.</note> All Infants having any Eſtates either in Poſſeſſion or Reverſion, whereof Entry ſhall not be made on their behalfs within the times aforeſaid, or where any falſe En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries ſhall be for them made, by any their Guardians, ends or Attorneys, ſhall have licenſe to make or rectifie their Entries, within ſix Months after they ſhall accompliſh the reſpective ages of 21. years; and alſo all perſons, who ſhall be abſent in other Countries, ſhall have the like time after their reſpective Returns to do the like.</p>
               <p n="34">34.
<note place="margin">Entries of Marriages.</note> All Marriages ſhall be entred in the reſpective Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rochial Regiſtries, where the ſame ſhall be ſolemnized, the ſame day that the ſame ſhall be ſolemnized, the married couple acknowledging the ſame, in preſence of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter and two other Inhabitants of the ſame Pariſh, who ſhall atteſt their knowledges of both the man and woman married together on their oaths, unleſs they ſhall be known to the Regiſter or his Deputy, who ſhall enter the ſame; and the Covenants and Conditions of the Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:119528:14"/>ſhall be entred alſo; and the Regiſter of every Pariſh, who ſhall enter the ſame, ſhall give Certificates to one or both the parties thereof, under the Seal of his REgiſtry, if the ſame ſhall be deſired.</p>
               <p n="35">35.
<note place="margin">Entries of Births.</note> The birth of every child ſhall be entered in the Parochial Regiſtry, where it ſhall be born, within one day after its birth, whether male or female: and the names of the father, if it be born legitimate; if not, of the mother, her quality and condition, and of the father named by her in time of her Travel, by the Oath of the Midwife and one witneſs more, who ſhall be preſent at the time of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livery.</p>
               <p n="36">36.
<note place="margin">Chriſtnings.</note> All Chriſtnings to be entred likewiſe in common form, as hath been accuſtomed.</p>
               <p>All Deaths and Burials ſhall be likewiſe entered in the ſeveral repective Parochial Regiſtries,
<note place="margin">Deaths and Burials.</note> where the ſame ſhall happen to be, by atteſtation of two known per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons reſiants within the ſame Pariſh, upon oath, if it be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired.</p>
               <p n="37">37.
<note place="margin">Wills and Teſtaments.</note> All Wills and Teſtaments ſhall be entred in the reſpective Regiſtries within whoſe Juriſdiction and Cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nizance the Eſtate of the deceaſed ſhall lie, within one Month after the ſeveral and reſpective death and deaths of every perſon and perſons, of what rank, quality or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition ſoever; and all gifts and bequeſts made, whether verbal or in writing, by the atteſtation of two credible perſons on oath; the perſons atteſting the ſame, being ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther known to the Regiſter to be of honeſt repute, or ſo atteſted to be by others to him known, as in other Caſes: all which circumſtances ſhall be particularly entred.</p>
               <p n="38">38.
<note place="margin">Hiring of Servants.</note> All and ſingular retainer or hiring all and every ſeveral and reſpective ſervants, whether Apprentices or hired ſervants, ſhall by the ſeveral and reſpective Maſters or Miſtreſſes hiring or retaining the ſame, be ſeverally and reſpectively entred, or cauſed to be entred in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective Parochial Regiſtries where their reſidence ſhall
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:119528:14"/>then be, together with the time for which ſuch retainer is to be; and the conſideration or wages to be given to the ſeveral and reſpective ſervant and ſervants, by the atteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the reſpective ſervants alſo ſubſcribing his, her or their names or marks in the Regiſtry: whereupon the Regiſter ſhall give Certificate or Certificates, to Maſter or Miſtreſs, and ſervant or ſervants deſiring the ſame, under his hand; which ſhall be ſufficient warranty, to compel ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice and reſpect from the ſervant, and wages and other conditions from the Maſter or Miſtreſs.</p>
               <p n="39">39.
<note place="margin">Fees for En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries with the National Register.</note> The Fees for all Entries of any Eſtate of Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance in the National Regiſtry, to be for any Eſtate in Fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimple 20 <hi> s. per</hi> page for the two firſt pages of the Entry, and 40 <hi>s.</hi> the page for every page more; for all Leaſes, Mortgages, Joyntures, Dowers or Debts, 10 <hi>s.</hi> for the firſt page, and 20 <hi>s.</hi> for every other following page, including the Fees of the Certificates alſo under hand.</p>
               <p n="40">40.
<note place="margin">Provincial Fees.</note> The Fees for all Entries of Inheritances in Fee in every Provincial Regiſtry, to be 10 <hi> s. per</hi> page for the two firſt pages, and 20 <hi> s. per</hi> page for every page more; and for all Leaſes, Mortgages, Joyntures, Dowers or Debts, 7 <hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi> for the firſt page, and 15 <hi>s.</hi> for every following page of every particular Entry; the Certificates under hand to be given for the ſame Fees, being included.</p>
               <p n="41">41.
<note place="margin">Sub-provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Fees.</note> The Fees for all Entries of Inheritances in Fee in every Sub-provincial Regiſtry to be 7 <hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi> for the firſt page, and 10 <hi> s. per</hi> page for every page more; and for all Leaſes, Mortgages, Joyntures, Dowers or Debts, 5 <hi>s.</hi> for the firſt page, and 7 <hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi> for every following page.</p>
               <p n="42">42.
<note place="margin">Parochial Fees.</note> The Fees for all Entries of Inheritances in Fee in every Parochial Regiſtry, to be 5 <hi>s.</hi> for the firſt page, and 7 <hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi> for every page more; and for all Leaſes, Mort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gages, Joyntures, Dowers or Debts, 2 <hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi> for the firſt page, and 5 <hi>s.</hi> for every following page: but in caſe any Entries of Debts, Leaſes, Mortgages, Joyntures or Dowries, ſhall not exceed ſix l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nes Regiſterially writ in the Parochial Regiſtry, the Fee of the Entry thereof ſhall
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:119528:15"/>but be 1 <hi>s.</hi> the ſeveral Fees for the ſeveral Certificates, to be made of any Entries, to be equal to the Regiſters Fees only for Entries as aforeſaid, out of which no part ſhall be accompted to the Commonwealth.</p>
               <p n="43">43.
<note place="margin">Fees for ſmall En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries.</note> The Fees for Entry and Certificate of every re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective Birth, Chriſtning, Death, and Burial, if it exceed not ſix lines in the Regiſterial Parochial Entry, the Fee thereof ſhall be 6 <hi>d.</hi> onely, as alſo the Entry of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainer of any Servant or Apprentice, if one Entry exceed not ſix lines; but if any Entry ſhall exceed ſix lines, then the Fees to be the ſame as are alotted <hi>per</hi> page.</p>
               <p n="44">44.
<note place="margin">Bargains not entred void.</note> No Money ſhall be recoverable upon any Bargain or Contract whatſoever, nor any Eſtate ſecured, unleſs the ſame be reſpectively entred in due form, in the ſeveral and reſpective Regiſtries, within whoſe limits and juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions the ſame ſhall be, within the reſpective times afore-ſpecified.</p>
               <p n="45">45.
<note place="margin">Fee of the National Registers Seal.</note> The Fee of the Seal of the National Regiſtry, in all Caſes of ſettlement of any Eſtate, Leaſe, Mortgage, Joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture or Dower, ſhall be 5 <hi>li.</hi> in all caſes of Debt not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding 2000 <hi>li.</hi> 50 <hi>s.</hi> But if the Debt exceed 2000 <hi>li.</hi> the Fee of the Seal ſhall be 5 <hi>li.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="46">46.
<note place="margin">Of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincial Seal</note> The Fee of each Provincial Seal, in all caſes of ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlement of Eſtates as aforeſaid, ſhall be 50 <hi>s.</hi> in all caſes of Debt, 25 <hi>s.</hi> 
               </p>
               <p n="47">47.
<note place="margin">Of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provincial.</note> The Fee of each Sub-provincial Seal, in all caſes of ſettlement of any Eſtates as aforeſaid, ſhall be 25 <hi>s.</hi> and in all Caſes of Debt, Mortgage, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 12 <hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi> 
               </p>
               <p n="48">48.
<note place="margin">Of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rochial.</note> The Fee of each Parochial Seal for ſettlement of any Eſtate, to be 10 <hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi> and of Debt, to be 5 <hi>s.</hi> 
               </p>
               <p n="49">49.
<note place="margin">Fees to the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth for the Natio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Seal.</note> In the National Regiſtry three fourth parts of the Fees for the Seal ſhall be to the Commonwealth, &amp; a fourth part to the Regiſter his Aſſiſtants and Clerks; for all En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries of each two firſt pages of every particular Entry, and for all the following pages, an eighth part only for En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries.</p>
               <p n="50">50.
<note place="margin">For the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincial Seal.</note> In each Provincial Regiſtry, three fourth parts of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:119528:15"/>the Fees for the Entries, and for Seals alſo, ſhall be to the Commonwealth, and the fourth to the Regiſter his Aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants and Clerks.</p>
               <p n="51">51.
<note place="margin">For the Sub-provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Seal.</note> In each Sub-provincial Regiſtry two parts of three of the Fees of Entries and Seal ſhall be to the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, the third to the Regiſter.</p>
               <p n="52">52. In each Parochial Regiſtry,
<note place="margin">For the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rochial Seal</note> two parts of three of the Fees of the Seal to the Commonwealth, the third and all the Fees of Entries to be to the Regiſter his Deputy and Clerks.</p>
               <p n="53">53.
<note place="margin">National Atturneys.</note> Every Clerk Aſſiſtant or Deputy to the National Regiſter, ſhall have ſix ſworn Atturneys or Meſſengers, whoſe care ſhall be to tranſmit the ſeveral Certificates by him made, to the ſeveral Regiſters of the Provinces, to whom the ſame ſhall be directed within the times limit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and ſhall likewiſe Solicite the Cauſes of all Suitors in the Regiſterial Court hereafter to be mentioned, and ſhall have for every Cauſe for every Court-day to be kept in the ſame buſineſs, for Fee, beſides all charges, 7 <hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi> and no more.</p>
               <p n="54">54.
<note place="margin">Provincial Atturneys Fees.</note> Every Clerk aſſiſtant in each reſpective Provincial Regiſtry ſhall have three Atturneys or Meſſengers, who ſhall carefully tranſmit all Certificates to be made, to the ſeveral Regiſters, to whom they ſhall be directed, within the times limitted; and ſhall alſo Solicite the Cauſes of Suitors; and for every Court-day any Cauſe is depending, ſhall have for every Cauſe any of them is imployed in, 5 <hi>s.</hi> for Fee, and no more; beſides all charges and expences.</p>
               <p n="55">55.
<note place="margin">Sub-provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Attur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neys Fees.</note> Each Sub-Provincial Regiſtry ſhall have two At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turneys, who ſhall do the ſame work, and for every Court-day ſhall have Fee in every Cauſe 4 <hi>s.</hi> beſides all charges and expences.</p>
               <p n="56">56. Each Parochial Regiſter ſhall have two Atturneys,
<note place="margin">Parochial Atturneys Fees.</note> whoſe Fee ſhall be for every Court-day 3 <hi>s.</hi> beſides charges; they alſo ſhall do the like work as the other fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned Atturneys ſhall do.</p>
               <p n="57">57.
<note place="margin">Puniſhment of Atturneys neglect.</note> If any Atturney (through fraud or neglect) ſhall
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:119528:16"/>prejudice any Client for want of care in proſecuting his buſineſs, either in the Regiſtry or Court, he ſhall ſatisfie for all damage accruing to the party thereby; which if he ſhall not be able to do, he ſhall be diſmiſſed from his Place and Practice, and another choſen in his room, and the party grieved reſtored to the condition he was in before the neglect or fraud was committed.</p>
               <p n="58">58.
<note place="margin">Election of Deouty Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſters.</note> The ſeveral Clerks aſſiſtant in every Regiſtry ſhall be choſen by the reſpective Regiſters under whom they are to officiate, who ſhall take ſecurity from them, give directions to them, and be reſponſible for them.</p>
               <p n="59">59.
<note place="margin">Election of Atturneys.</note> Each Clerk aſſiſtant ſhall make choice of one Attur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, and the Regiſter two in the Provincial Regiſtries: that one choſen by the Clerk aſſiſtants ſhall be approved by the Regiſter: each Clerk Aſſiſtant in the National Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtry to chuſe two Atturneys, to be approved by the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſter, and the Regiſter to chuſe and appoint all the reſt; the other Atturneys in the Sub-provincial and Parochial Regiſtries, to be appointed by the reſpective Regiſters of the ſeveral Sub-provinces and Pariſhes where they are to officiate.</p>
               <p n="60">60.
<note place="margin">Atturneys to give ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</note> Each ſeveral Regiſter ſhall reſpectively take ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity from every Atturney elected or admitted by him to practice within his Regiſtry, truly and diligently to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>have himſelf, according to ſuch Rules and Directions as he ſhall from time to time receive: And to the end none may be ignorant of his Office, each Regiſter ſhall have a Table of Directions and Fees hung up in his Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, to the view of all who ſhall have any occaſion there; wherein ſhall be particularized every thing each Officer under him is to do, and what his Fees for the ſame ſhall be; that none may plead Ignorance for excuſe, and that every party wronged may know where to finde re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſe.</p>
               <p n="61">61. Each ſeveral Regiſter, Clerk Aſſiſtant and Attur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney in the National Regiſtry, and each ſeveral and reſpective Provincial Regiſtry, ſhall be allowed and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rized
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:119528:16"/>by Parliament to their ſeveral and reſpective Offices; and for the due execution of their places ſeverally and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectively, ſhall take ſuch oath as the Parliament ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point.</p>
               <p n="62">62. Each Sub-provincial and Parochial Rgiſter ſhall be allowed and authorized by Parliament; and each Clerk, Aſſiſtant or Deputy and Atturney under them reſpectively to be imployed, ſhall be allowed of and authorized by the ſeveral Provincial Regiſters, under whoſe reſpective juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions they ſhall be reſpectively, and to take ſuch oath as ſhall be appointed by Parliament.</p>
               <p n="63">63. In all Markets and Fairs,
<note place="margin">Tolls.</note> the Toll ſhall be kept by the Town-Regiſter, where diſtinct Entries ſhall be made of all Cattel ſold (at the peril of the Buyer) with known Vouchers who ſhall atteſt the ſale, who in caſe of que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion to be made after, ſhall be reſponſible for the ſame, or the value thereof double, to be imployed as aforeſaid; to which end, entry ſhall be made of the names, qualities and habitations of all Sellers and their Vouchers, and the Cattel and marks, with the names of the Buyers, and the Prices paid.</p>
               <p>Due care being of all the Premiſes had, all perſons E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, whether in annual Revenue, or Money, ſhall be known, whereby all publique Aſſeſments and Taxes may be equally born, and all perſons known who ſhall have reſponſible Eſtates fit to undergo any Imployment for the Republique: no danger ſhall be, or very little (if care be taken) of any perſon being defrauded or abuſed by any falſe Titles, nor any dormant Titles prejudice any future Purchaſer or Purchaſers. No perſon having his Eſtate ſo well known to the Republique, ſhall attempt any altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Inſurrection or Rebellion, but ſhall preſently be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered; and thereby his Eſtate, if not his perſon, ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpond for the offence. With many other conveniencies not particularized, much tending to the Publique Weale.</p>
               <p>For the doing of all which, little trouble extraordinary,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:119528:17"/>nor any conſiderable charge can be to any particular party or Intereſt in the Nation, neither can the ſame be valuable in reſpect of the ſettlement thereby to be obtained, out of which yet there will ariſe a conſiderable Revenue to the Republique; and the extraordinary expences of Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vels and Lawyers Fees ſhall be taken off, whereby the Country is at preſent much damnified for the benefit on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of a few, and thoſe of no conſiderable intereſt in the Nation, ſeldom at any time helpful, bur frequently both to Prince and People bur then ſome, who ſhall notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing be hereafter better provided for then now they are, and at an eaſier charge to the Country by far. Whereby ſeveral ſhall be encouraged to enable themſelves to be fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted therefore.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The Third Days Work.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The third brings unknown births to life,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>By giving Laws for ending strife.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Let Regiſters their work attend,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Whilſt we endeavour Laws to mend.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p n="1">1.
<note place="margin">Law.</note> ALL former precedent Cuſtoms notwithſtanding, let one Law be through the whole Nation, whereby the Publique Intereſt may be beſt ſupported, and each pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate moderately provided for; and that one Prodigal Rio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous perſon may not conſume the Patrimony of a whole Family, neither any one lord it over his brethern, who not being educated in provident ways, many times (to ſupply themſelves according to their Chimerical. Gentilities, conſiſting of nothing but Idlneſs) turn Hectors, Highway<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, Trapanners, and what not? to ſupport themſelves in
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:119528:17"/>that looſeneſs they have been by their improvident Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents or Anceſtors trained up in: but that each may be in ſome meaſure participant of his Anceſtors induſtry, let all Eſtates not exceeding 100 <hi>li. per annum</hi> (where a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal Eſtate ſhall not be left anſwerable thereto) be diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted amongſt the children as follows; that is to ſay, to each ſon two parts, or twice as much as ſhall be to any daughter, and to each daughter 1/3, or half as much as ſhall be to any ſon; only the eldeſt ſon, or he whom the father ſhall think moſt worthy, when ſuch diviſion ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll be made, to have the firſt choice, and the youngeſt the ſecond: and ſo likewiſe the daughters.</p>
               <p n="2">2.
<note place="margin">Settlement of Estates.</note> But where the Eſtate perſonal ſhall equalize the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance of 100 <hi>li. per annum,</hi> there the eldeſt ſon, or the moſt worthy in the fathers apprehenſion, ſhall have the 100 <hi>li.</hi> Inheritance, and the reſt be divided as aforeſaid; and ſo of all greater Eſtates, not more then one half de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcending to the eldeſt: only if there ſhall be but two ſons, and no daughter, there the elder to have two parts, and the younger a third: if two ſons and one daughter, the eld<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt ſon to have half; the other half to be two parts to the ſon, and a third to the daughter: if two ſons and two daughters, half to the eldeſt, and the remaining half to be half thereof to the younger ſon, and the other remaining half between the two daughters, equally to be divided. Theſe diviſions to be, where at leaſt 200 <hi>li. per annum,</hi> or 100 <hi>li. per annum,</hi> and 2000 <hi>li.</hi> in money or perſonal Eſtate ſhall be left by the Anceſtor. The like proportion to be ſtill held in all greater Eſtates. The wives Eſtate to be as now, either a third during life only, or ſuch pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion as ſhall be agreed upon before Marriage: which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement entered in the proper Regiſtry, ſhall be valid, and good to all ends and purpoſes.</p>
               <p n="3">3. In all Caſes of deſcent,
<note place="margin">Wives Joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</note> the elder to be preferred be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the younger, and the ſon before the daughter; the next Uncle or Cozen by the whole bloud, before any other by the half bloud, according to the deſcents now in uſe.</p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:119528:18"/>
               <p n="4">4.
<note place="margin">Copie-hold made Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold.</note> All Copyhold Eſtates to be made free by reaſonable Compoſitions with the Lords; as where Fines are certain, payable upon every change, there the value of two Fines and an half to redeem the ſervitude; and where Compoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions have not been formerly made, according to the ſame proportion, conſidering the Lords Intereſt equivalent to what it is; and likewiſe all Reliefs and Hariots to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded for, and for ever after to ceaſe.</p>
               <p n="5">5. All Lords of Mannors keeping conſtant Courts, Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron and Courts Leet, or either of them, ſhall diſcontinue the ſame; and ſhall have the value of the profits of their Courts reſponded out of the immediate profits of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtry, within whoſe limits the ſame Mannor ſhall wholly lie and be comprehended, according as ſhall have been made thereof for ten years laſt paſt; and all Hundred-Courts to ceaſe, and be for ever hereafter diſconti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued.</p>
               <p>All antient ſervices to any Lords of Mannors to ceaſe,
<note place="margin">Service to be compoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for.</note> but the Rents to continue; and upon Entries thereof in the reſpective Regiſtries, to be aſcertained and ſecured by the Law of the Regiſtry only; and all other Laws, and by-Laws for recovery thereof, to ceaſe, and be of no uſe for ever hereafter: but where any ſervices are valuable in money, the value thereof at ten years purchaſe to be paid for Compoſition: all Compoſitions to be entred in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective Regiſtries whereon the ſame are dependant, or within whoſe reſpective limits the ſame lie.</p>
               <p>In all Caſes, the Teſtimony of any Regiſter under Seal of the Regiſtry, to be preferred before any other, the ſame being taken and certified according to the rules afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid.</p>
               <p n="6">6.
<note place="margin">Married women ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe.</note> It ſhall be lawful for any married woman, of what de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, rank or quality ſoever (who ſhall have any Eſtate of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance in her own diſpoſal, by acknowledging her con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent thereto before the Regiſter under whoſe immediate Cognizance the Eſtate ſhall lie, or before the Parochial Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſter where ſhe ſhall live (he being thereto by the proper
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:119528:18"/>Regiſter authorized) and to whom the ſame ſhall be again certified and proceeded in as in other Caſes) to give, grant, and at her will diſpoſe of all or any ſuch Bſtate; which ſhall be good in Law to all intents and purpoſes.</p>
               <p n="7">7. All Wills ſhall be proved,
<note place="margin">Probate of Wills.</note> and adminiſtration granted by the Regiſterial Court, within whoſe juriſdiction the party deceaſed lived at the time of death; and by the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſter of the ſame Court certified under Seal, which ſhall be entred with the ſeveral and reſpective Regiſters, with whom any Eſtate granted by ſuch diſpoſal ſhall lie, within one month after the burial of all, every or any perſon or, perſons whatſoever; and in no caſe to be deferred paſt the fourth Court-day, and then confirmation thereof to paſs under the Seal of the Regiſtry where the ſame ſhall be done: in this Caſe the value to be conſidered as in other Caſes relating to the juriſdiction of Courts.</p>
               <p n="8">8.
<note place="margin">Appeal be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> No Appeal ſhall in any caſe be brought before Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment given; but after Judgement, either party that is wronged may bring a Writ of Appeal from the next ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>intendent Court, and Execution ſhall be ſtayed till the matter thereof ſhall be heard in the ſame Court, to which the Appeal ſhall be made, which ſhall be the third Court<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day after return of the firſt Writ, which ſhall be executed by ſummons of ſome Court-Officer in perſon, at leaſt four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen days before the day of appearance; where the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs ſhall be determined without any further Appeal by either party: and execution ſhall be awarded upon the Decree or Order of that Court, not to be Repealed. This Caſe of Appeal not to extend to any contemner of Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, as aforeſaid.</p>
               <p n="9">9.
<note place="margin">Sheriffs.</note> In every County or Province a Sheriff ſhall be annu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally elected by Parliament, who ſhall within one month af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his appointment, ſubſtitute in each Sub-province in his County or Province, a Deputy, which ſhall be approved by the next Provincial Regiſterial Court, in which the Sheriffs election ſhall be ſubordinate to the Court; and no one perſon to continue in that place more then one year;
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:119528:19"/>the old Officers for the precedent year, to officiate till the new ones for the next year ſhall be approved on, and thereto Authorized by the Provincial Regiſtry.</p>
               <p n="10">10.
<note place="margin">Conſtable.</note> In each Parochial Regiſtry ſhall be likewiſe every year elected an Officer, by the name of Conſtable, who ſhall have chief care of preſerving the Peace; and ſhall have the execution of all Writs iſſued from the Parochial Regiſter, other then ſuch Summons as are elſewhere di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected to be done by the Atturneys. For choice of this Officer, ſhall be preſented three names by the precedent Conſtable to the Sub-provincial Regiſtry, who ſhall chuſe and Authorize one of them Conſtable for the next year.</p>
               <p n="11">11.
<note place="margin">Manner of Elections.</note> That no perſon ſhall be elected to the ſame Office, either of Sheriff, Sheriffs Deputy or Conſtable for the ſame liberty, before ſeven years ſhall be elapſed after his ſerving thereof, before he ſhall be new elected, but that ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral perſons be imployed therein from time to time; and that no perſons ſhall be elected to ſerve any ſuch Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, who ſhall not have Eſtate reſponſible to the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique for what ſhall be intruſted with them.</p>
               <p n="12">12.
<note place="margin">Collections.</note> That all Collections which ſhall be from time to time made and impoſed on the Country, ſhall be collect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Conſtables, and by them entred in their reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive Parochial Regiſtries; and then paid to the Sheriffs Sub-provincial Deputy, and by him and every of them en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred in their reſpective Regiſtries; and then paid to the Sheriff; and by the ſeveral Sheriffs, to the Treaſury of the Revenue to be appointed by Parliament for receipt thereof.</p>
               <p n="13">13.
<note place="margin">Juſtices of Peace.</note> That one or more perſons of quality in every Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>province be and execute the place of Juſtices of the Peace, and keep general Quarter-Seſſions as is accuſtom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and alſo private monthly Seſſions as often as need ſhall require; and at each general Quarter-Seſſions, the Sheriff or under-Sheriff for that Province ſhall be preſent, and alſo the ſeveral Conſtables or their ſufficient deputies
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:119528:19"/>for the ſeveral Pariſhes, and alſo one or more of the Church-wardens for every Pariſh, to preſent what ſhall be amiſs within their ſeveral and reſpective Liberties, which ſhall not be taken care of or duely executed by the reſpective Regiſterial Courts: and the ſaid Juſtices ſhall have power to convent before them all Offenders, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo all Regiſters, Clerks Aſſiſtants or Deputies, Atturneys and other inferiour Officers within the ſame Riding or Liberty for which the Seſſions ſhall be kept, and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Miſdemeanors and breaches of the Peace whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, and puniſh the Offenders, and regulate the ſame, as well as any ſuperiour Court ſhall have power to do.</p>
               <p>Each Conſtable ſhall annually elect under him a ſubſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute in each Village, Hamlet and Townſhip within the Pariſh, who ſhall be approved of and authorized by the Parochial Regiſterial Court, whereby they ſhall be ſworn truly to execute all Summons, and other precepts to them ſent, and to endeavour to preſerve the Peace, and keep good Order; and if any ſhall refuſe ſo to do within their limits, to return their names and offences to the Conſtable, who ſhall for his year uſe the power of a Magiſtrate for puniſhment of all Offenders contrary to Law.</p>
               <p n="14">14.
<note place="margin">Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardens.</note> Each Pariſh ſhall yearly elect ſo many Church-war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens as have been accuſtomed, who ſhall be ſworn (by the Regiſterial Court) to take care for the repairing &amp; beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying of the Church &amp; Church-yard wall, Gates and Stiles, and to provide for convenient and decent furniture for the Church, <hi>viz.</hi> for Books, Cuſhions for the Pulpit, Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet for the Table, Chalices or Cups for the Communion, Candleſticks and Candles for celebration of Prayers. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vening and Morning in Winter; Bells, Belſtrings, and Clock, with the Appurtenances; and ſhall ſee that all ſeats be conveniently placed, and controul all irregularities in the Church: they ſhall alſo take care for amendment of all Highways in their Pariſh, and for providing for ſuch poor as ſhall not be able to help themſelves; for there ſhall be no beggers permitted, but if any ſo do, they ſhall
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:119528:20"/>be ſent by the next Officer to the Conſtable, and by him ſent to the common Work-houſe, unleſs ſecurity be given to offend no more. For doing of all which, they ſhall im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe ſuch Aſſeſments as ſhall be convenient to be collect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and disburſed to and for ſeveral uſes, by the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable, who at his going out of Office ſhall accompt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Regiſterial Court for all receipts and payments, and ſhall within ſix days pay all Moneys remaining in his hands, to the ſucceeding Conſtable for the next year: which if he ſhall refuſe, diſtreſs or ſeizure of his Eſtate real or perſonal ſhall be made by the ſucceeding Conſtable, by Warrant under the Regiſters Seal: and if any Conſtable ſhall disburſe more for any the uſes aforeſaid then he ſhall collect, he ſhall (upon clearing his accompts, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance thereof by the Regiſterial Court, and entry thereof with the Regiſter) be re-imburſed the ſame by the next Conſtable within one month; which ſhall be allowed in his Accompts. And if any ſucceeding Conſtable ſhall refuſe to make payment of any ſuch disburſements to the preceding Conſtable (the ſame being allowed and entred in the Regiſtry) an Action of Debt ſhall lie, to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered by way of diſtreſs by the Sheriffs deputy in the Sub-province, and no allowance ſhall be made in his ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compts of any charges expended therein. All Aſſeſments to be impoſed by the Church-wardens aforeſaid, ſhall be entred in the Regiſtry, and by the Regiſters ordered to be collected, ſignifying for what uſe or uſes the ſame are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, and not otherways.</p>
               <p n="15">15.
<note place="margin">Actions of Treſpaſs and Slander</note> All Actions of Treſpaſs and Slander ſhall be heard in the Parochial Court firſt, where the ſame ſhall be committed; and, if the ſame ſhall be of greater con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment then the Court hath Cognizance, be tranſmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the next ſuperior Judicature; but if it ſhall not be of greater value in the eſtimation of the Court, then the Court hath power to judge of, judgement ſhall be therein given, and execution done thereupon, as in other caſes.</p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:119528:20"/>
               <p n="16">16. In all caſes where Murther,
<note place="margin">Murther, Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlaughter and Rape.</note> Man-ſlaughter or Rape ſhall be committed, the offenders ſhall be examined before the Parochial Magiſtrate where the parties ſhall be appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended, or the fault committed; &amp; ſo many as ſhall be found guilty, ſhall be ſent by the Conſtable to the Sheriffs Depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and by him to the Provincial Goal, there to be kept in work as ſhall be directed, till their legal delivery thence: &amp; in none of theſe caſes Bail ſhall be admitted, but to be try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Juries as hath been accuſtomed; and to ſuffer death, if found guilty, without benefit of pardon or Reprieve.</p>
               <p n="17">17. In all manner of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>heft, Robbery,
<note place="margin">Theft, Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery, Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenage and Fraud.</note> Couſenage and Fraud. the Offenders ſhall be examined before the Paro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chial Magiſtrates; and if found guilty, threefold reſtitution ſhall be made, to be diſpoſed one part to ſatisfie the party wronged, one part to the common ſtock of the Town, and one other part to the Conſtable, for reparation of High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways; which if the party refuſe, and no diſtreſs ſhall be found to ſatisfie the Law, the body of the offender ſhall be committed to the cuſtody of the Maſter of the Work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe, or elſe ſent to the place from whence they came, if aliens, with Certificate of their offence, and there to be imployed, and to have two parts only of their gets allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for their maintenance, and a third to be to the uſe of the common ſtock. The detainer or ſending away, to be at the election of the Parochial Magiſtracy, where ſuch of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender or offenders ſhall be apprehended and tryed as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid.</p>
               <p n="18">18.
<note place="margin">Defamation</note> All falſe accuſations on purpoſe to defame any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, ſhall be heavily puniſhed by the immediate Magiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, where the offence ſhall be committed; and in this caſe no Appeal to lie or be admitted: and where the offence ſhall deſerve greater puniſhment then the Parochial Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate may inflict, (who may not exceed 10 <hi>li.</hi> in any caſe) the ſame ſhall be certified to the Sub-provincial Magiſtrate; and if it require, thence to the Provincial, but not further. All ambiguous caſes ſhall be tranſmitted with the evidences to the next ſuperior Magiſtracy, and ſo
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:119528:21"/>on to the Parliament, if no inferiour Court ſhall be free to give judgement therein.</p>
               <p n="19">19.
<note place="margin">Fighting, quarrelling and break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Peace.</note> All fighting, quarrelling, and breaking of the Peace, ſhall be examined and puniſhed by the Parochial Magiſtracy, where the ſame ſhall be committed, and ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction made to the party wronged without delay; whereto the offenders ſhall be compelled according to the order of the Court; and for all bruiſings and beatings, ſatisfaction ſhall be made as the Laws in being direct.</p>
               <p>If any Maſter or Miſtreſs ſhall immoderately correct any child or ſervant,
<note place="margin">Masters and ſervants</note> the Court Parochial ſhall puniſh the offender.</p>
               <p n="20">20. If any child or ſervant ſhall refuſe to do their du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, or ſhall ſtrike or quarrel with their Parents, Maſters or Miſtreſſes, the Court ſhall heavily puniſh ſuch offences; and if any Apprentices ſhall ſo do, they ſhall ſerve a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble term, and any other ſervant a double year for the ſame wages. No ſon or daughter vilifying or ſlighting their Parents, or either of them, ſhall be capable of inheriting any thing from either father or mother after their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective deaths.</p>
               <p n="21">21. Let ſo many Regiſterial Courts be erected as there are Regiſtries, <hi>viz.</hi> to every Regiſtry it's Court, with Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers Fees, and Rules to walk by, for the eaſe and profit of each particular intereſt.</p>
               <p n="22">22.
<note place="margin">National Judges.</note> Let twelve Judges learned in the Laws be appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Parliament to attend the National Regiſterial Court, to which let all great cauſes be reduced, any three whereof, with the Regiſter or one Aſſiſtant, ſhall have pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to hear and determine all matters of controverſie; and let the three Bars in <hi>Weſtminſter</hi>-Hall be the places of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicature; and the ſeveral rooms adjacent, Offices for the Regiſters, <hi>viz.</hi> each two Circuits their proper Court, for trial of all grand Cauſes ariſing within their limits; and in other mixt caſes where one party ſhall live in one Courts juriſdiction, and one in another, there the Cauſe to be heard in the third Court, where neither parties intereſt is more concerned then the other.</p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:119528:21"/>
               <p n="23">23. Let only two Vacations be in the whole year, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Vacations.</note> one from the firſt of <hi>December,</hi> to the tenth of <hi>February,</hi> the other from the laſt day of <hi>May</hi> till the firſt day of <hi>September,</hi> yearly; in which Summer-Vacations the Judges to ride the ſeveral Circuits as now, to viſit the ſeveral Regiſtries, calling before them all the Regiſters of every Province, and hearing all complaints againſt any Regiſter, Clerk, Atturney or other Officer, and puniſhing all offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders; and alſo for determining all grand and difficult Cauſes, and Cauſes of Appeals, where any ſuch ſhall be depending.</p>
               <p n="24">24.
<note place="margin">Terms and proceedings.</note> Let all the reſt of the year be two continued Terms, wherein the Judges ſhall ſit as often as cauſe ſhall require; the firſt day of every Term being a Return-day, and the third day day of Appearance; before which third day, the Plaintiff in every Action ſhall enter his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration with the Regiſter, whereto the Defendant ſhall plead within ten days, and enter his Plea with the ſame Clerk; whereupon order ſhall be given for exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Witneſſes, and depoſitions ſent into the ſeveral Countries to the reſpective Parochial Regiſters within whoſe limits the ſeveral Witneſſes ſhall live, whoſe Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination ſhall be taken, and returned within one month after the Pleading aforeſaid; and entry made thereof alſo with the ſame Regiſterial Clerk by whom the firſt Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons was awarded, with whom all the entries in the ſame Cauſe ſhall be made. The fourth day after return of the examinations aforeſaid, the Cauſe ſhall be heard, (if it be not the Lords day, if ſo,
<note place="margin">Judgement.</note> the day next following) and Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhall be given and entred the ſame day with the ſame Clerk: and the ſixth day after Judgement, Executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſhall be awarded, not to recalled, unleſs the parties a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree in the mean time, and enter their Agreement with the ſame Clerk. In caſe of any Witneſſes abſence on the Defendants behalf, upon warrantable occaſions made appear upon oath to any Parochial Regiſter, by whom the Witneſs or Witneſſes were to be examined, a ſecond day
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:119528:22"/>to be given, upon the Defendants payment of coſts for examination, not to defer the hearing above one month longer then it was to have been.</p>
               <p n="25">25.
<note place="margin">Provincial Judges.</note> Let two Judges be appointed by Parliament to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend every Provincial Regiſterial Court; that one Judge with the Regiſter, and one Clerk aſſiſtant at leaſt, ſhall be preſent when all matters ſhall be heard; and in all difficult matters, one Judge at leaſt ſhall be called out of the next Province, who ſhall have notice ſent to him by the Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, at leaſt ſix days before the day of hearing ſhall be: his whole expences of his journey and tarriance to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frayed by the Regiſters by whom he ſhall be ſent for, and to be allowed him in his accompts to the Publique: And to hold Pleas of all Debts not exceeding 1000 <hi>li.</hi> and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates under 1000 <hi>li. per annum,</hi> lying within the ſame Province.</p>
               <p n="26">26.
<note place="margin">Courts and proceedings.</note> Every Month ſhall be a Court Provincial kept in every reſpective Province, in the Middle of the week, <hi>viz.</hi> upon Tueſday in every month; and if occaſion ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, to be continued the Wedneſday alſo, and no longer: during which time only, Summons ſhall be given, which within ten days at fantheſt ſhall be executed, and appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance given the next Court-day; at which time a Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhall be entred by the Plaintiff; within three days after, which the Defendant ſhall plead, and thereupon or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders be ſent for examination of Witneſſes, and return of their depoſitions before the next Court-day, and then the Cauſe ſhall be heard,
<note place="margin">Judgement.</note> and Judgement given and entred; and unleſs the parties agree, and enter their agreement be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the next Court-day, execution ſhall be awarded, not to be deferred or reverſed.</p>
               <p n="27">27.
<note place="margin">Sub-provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Judges.</note> The Judges in every Sub-province, ſhall be the Regiſter and his Aſſiſtant; the Miniſter of the Pariſh where the Regiſters Court ſhall be kept, and the Sheriffs deputy; and in all Cauſes of difficulty, one or more Juſtice of Peace ſhall be called to aſſiſt, who ſhall have at leaſt ſix days notice. Whereof alwaies ſome two, with the Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:119528:22"/>or Aſſiſtant, ſhall be preſent at all Trials and hearings of all matters in variance between party and party.</p>
               <p n="28">28.
<note place="margin">Courts.</note> The Sub-provincial Courts ſhall be kept every Friday three weeks; the Proceeds as in the Provincial, and the hearing the third Court-day, and execution the fourth, except as before; and to hold pleas of all Debts not exceeding 100 <hi>li.</hi> principal, and all Eſtates un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der 100 <hi>li. per annum,</hi> lying within the ſame Sub-pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince.</p>
               <p n="29">29.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Parochial Judges, Courts,</hi> &amp;c.</note> The Judges in the ſeveral Pariſh-Courts ſhall be the Regiſter, the Miniſter, the Conſtable and Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardens for the time being; whereof in all hearings two to be preſent with the Regiſter or his Deputy: the ſeveral Courts to be kept every Thurſday fourtnight, and all mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to be brought to be hearing the third Court-day as before; to hold pleas of all Debts not exceeding 10 <hi>li.</hi> principal, and all Eſtates under 10 <hi>li. per annum,</hi> lying in the ſame Pariſh.</p>
               <p n="30">30. All Summons ſhall be granted (upon motion of the party or his Atturney,
<note place="margin">Summons.</note> giving ſecurity to defray the charges of the party to be ſummoned, if his Action be not good, and cauſe juſt) by the reſpective Regiſters their Clerks Aſſiſtant or Deputies, in writing under their hands: to which if appearance ſhall be given either in perſon or by Atturney, proceedings ſhall be made as before: if no appearance ſhall be given, a ſecond Summons ſhall be granted under the Seal of the Regiſtry; to which if no ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance ſhall be given, Judgement ſhall be given the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond day of Appearance reſpectively, and entred in the Court-Regiſtry: and if agreement intervene not before the next Court-day, and be entred with the Regiſter, exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution ſhall be granted, and the Regiſters Seal put there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to; Not to be reverſed, nor any Appeal admitted.</p>
               <p n="31">31.
<note place="margin">Execution of Summons</note> Execution of Summons ſhall be done by the ſeveral Parochial Officers, within whoſe Pariſhes the parties to be ſummoned ſhall reſide or inhabit, as follows: each Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficer to whom any Summons ſhall be directed, ſhall the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:119528:23"/>next day at furtheſt, if it be not the Lords day, if ſo, the next day after (if it may not be done the day of his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt thereof) take two next Neighhours to the parties to be ſummoned with him, and ſhall go to the houſe or houſes where the party or parties ſhall live; and if the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty or parties there be to be met with, he ſhall give him, her or them a Copy thereof in writing; if not, he ſhall leave the ſame with ſome body in the houſe to give him, her or them, at his, her or their return; or acquaint him, her or them with it: and if no body be found about the houſe, he ſhall leave the Summons with the next Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, and ſhall make return to the Regiſtry of what he hath done, upon his own and the other perſons oaths who were with him.</p>
               <p n="32">32.
<note place="margin">Contempts.</note> All Summons ſhall be given in the day-time, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the hours of eight aforenoon, and four afternoon, in all Caſes whatſoever; and if any party to be ſummoned, ſhall threaten, affront, offer abuſe to, or hide or conceal him or her ſelf from any Officer ſo ſent with any Summons as aforeſaid, the Witneſſes ſhall upon their oaths make en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try thereof with the Regiſter; which entry ſhall be made by the Regiſter <hi>gratis;</hi> and upon complaint thereof to the Court by the Officer, the delinquents ſhall be ſeverely puniſhed according to the quality of the offender; and till ſatisfaction be made according to the Cenſure of the Court, appearance ſhal not be accepted: to the end all perſons may give obedience to the Magiſtracy. And if appearance be not given, proceeding ſhall paſs by default, as before.</p>
               <p n="33">33.
<note place="margin">Manner of granting Summons, and to whom.</note> All Summons granted by the National or any Provincial Regiſter, ſhall by the party who deſires the ſame, or his Atturney, be ſent to the Regiſter of the Pariſh, where every party to be ſummoned ſhall live, within ſix days after the date thereof; who ſhall the next day at fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſt give notice thereof to one of the Atturneys, who ſhall conſtantly attend that Court, who ſhall execute the ſame as aforeſaid, and earefully tranſmit what the Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:119528:23"/>ſhall direct to the Regiſter or Atturney National or Provincial from whom the ſame was received, who (upon receipt thereof) ſhall with care and ſpeed, enter the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn and execution thereof: which being under the Paro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chial Regiſters Seal, ſhall be ſufficient and warrantable to all intents and purpoſes.</p>
               <p n="34">34. In all Caſes where need ſhall require,
<note place="margin">Examinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes.</note> Interrogato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries ſhall be ſent from the National or Provincial Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, before whom any Cauſe ſhall depend, to the Regiſter of the Pariſh where the party lives, or parties to be exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined, with direction to examine and return the Depoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, within ſuch time as ſhall be limitted: all interrogato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries to be ſent away within two days after the pleadings ended, and to be executed by every Parochial Regiſter within ſix days after receipt thereof, if the parties to be examined be to be found in his Regiſtry; if not, to make return thereof, or examine ſo many as ſhall be found, and return the depoſitions thereof, and abſence of the reſt, and upon what occaſion; and within two days after exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, return the ſame to the Regiſter from whom he firſt received them, by the care of one of his Atturneys: and in all caſes where Witneſſes live in the ſame Pariſh or Town, they ſhall be examined <hi>viva voce,</hi> in open Court, if able to appear there; if not, the Regiſter, his Clerk Aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant or Deputy ſhall attend them, and take their exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations at leaſt two days before the day of return.</p>
               <p n="35">35.
<note place="margin">Execution of Summons</note> Execution of all Summons in the Sub-provincial and Parochial Courts for appearance at their own Courts, ſhall be by the Sheriffs ſubſtitute, and the Conſtable for their reſpective Liberties to whom the ſame ſhall be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected, or by their reſpective deputies inhabiting in the ſame Villages or Hamlets where the partie to be ſummon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed lives; whereof return ſhall be made the next Court<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, upon the oath of the party imployed, and one Witneſs more inhabiting within the ſame Village: for in all caſes, upon the oaths of two Witneſſes ſhall every truth be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed; to which end, care ſhall be taken that perſons
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:119528:24"/>of quality be taken for witneſſes, who in caſe falſe teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony ſhall be proved to be given by them, ſhall make ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction to the party by ſuch falſe teſtimony wronged, according to the Judgement of the Court in that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half.</p>
               <p n="36">36.
<note place="margin">Execution of Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Decrees.</note> Execution of all Judgements, Decrees and Orders of the National, Provincial and Sub-provincial Courts, ſhall be done by the Sheriff, his deputy or ſubſtitute, within ſix days after his receipt thereof; and within ſix days more, return ſhall be made thereof, to the reſpective Regiſter who ſent the ſame.</p>
               <p n="37">37.
<note place="margin">Of Parochi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</note> Execution of all Parochial Judgements, Decrees and Orders ſhall be done by the Conſtable for the time being, or his ſubſtitute living within the ſame Village or Hamlet where execution is to be done; for which the Conſtable ſhall be reſponſible.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The Fourth Days Work.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>A Parliament well choſen,
<note place="margin">Parliament</note> ties</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The hands of all exormities.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>It beſt provides in publick caſe:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>So here it comes the next in place.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p n="1">1. LEt annually a Parliament be elected, and each per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon whoſe whole Eſtate ſhall be entred in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtry as aforeſaid, to be capable of electing or being elect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but none others: The Electors to have Eſtates of 5 <hi>li. per annum,</hi> or 100 <hi>li.</hi> in money or upwards, Entred and certified as aforeſaid.</p>
               <p n="2">2.
<note place="margin">Parochial elections.</note> Each firſt Court-day to be held in every Parochial Regiſtry, in <hi>January</hi> yearly, all the Inhabitants, Electors,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:119528:24"/>ſhall each perſonally preſent his Paper ſealed up to the Regiſter, wherein ſhall be written the names of two ſuch perſons only of that Pariſh, as he ſhall think moſt worthy to be Repreſentees at the publique election, without ſubſcription of his own name: all which Papers ſhall be put into a Box or Cheſt with a hole in the top, locked or ſealed with three ſeveral Locks or Seals; one Key or Seal whereof ſhall be kept by the Conſtable, one by the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, and a third by the Church-wardens of the ſame Pariſh, or ſome of them; and when all ſuch Papers ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived and put therein as aforeſaid, the Box to be opened, and the Papers alſo in preſence and open view of the Court; and five perſons who ſhall have moſt nominations in the Papers aforeſaid, ſhall be the Repreſentees of that Pariſh, in all publique elections and tranſactions for that year.</p>
               <p n="3">3.
<note place="margin">Sub-provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</note> The ſeveral Repeſentees of the ſeveral Pariſhes within each Sub-province, ſhall meet at the next Sub-pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincial Court for that Hundred, and ſhall there give their Papers ſealed, to the Box, to be kept under the ſeals ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral of the Regiſter, the Sheriffs deputy, and the next Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of Peace for the time being, with each two names written therein: and when all the Papers ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, the Box and Papers ſhall be opened and examined in open Court; and thoſe two perſons within that Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>province, who ſhall have moſt names, or be ofteneſt named in the Papers, ſhall be the Repreſentees of that Sub-pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince for that year.</p>
               <p n="4">4.
<note place="margin">Provincial elections.</note> The ſeveral Sub provincial Repreſentees ſhall the next Court-day to be held for that Province, meet at the Provincial Court, and there each ſhall give his Paper ſeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up, with two names only writ therein, to the like Box there to be kept by the Regiſter, the Sheriff, the Major of the Corporation where the Office ſhall be kept, and two Juſtices of the Peace, under their ſeveral locks or ſeals, till all the papers ſhall be received thereinto: and when all the Papers ſhall be received, the Box and Papers ſhall
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:119528:25"/>be opened, and four choſen who have moſt voices for the Repreſentees for that Province for that year. And for <hi>York</hi> ſix, <hi>viz.</hi> each Riding two.</p>
               <p n="5">5.
<note place="margin">Perſons e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected, to be Reſiants in the Country for which they are to be elected.</note> It is to be obſerved, that in each County or Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince, twice ſo many Repreſentees ſhall be elected, as are Clerks aſſiſtant to the Provincial Regiſter in that County; and ſo in the Province of <hi>York</hi> ſix. Repreſentees ſhall be choſen, <hi>viz.</hi> for each Riding one, who ſhall be Reſidents within the ſame Riding; and ſo in the reſpective Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces where four are only to be, they ſhall be for each Clerk aſſiſtants juriſdiction two, who ſhall be reſident within the ſame; and no perſon ſhall ſerve for any other place, then where his conſtant reſidence ſhall be Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>their ſhall any perſon be elected who ſhall be ſolicited for, either by Letter, Meſſage or otherways, from any Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, Governours, or Commanders, of what rank, quality or condition ſoever; but that upon appearance thereof to the Court, all ſuch ſhall be rejected as unworthy, and not to be admitted of two years to be elected: To the end all elections may be free. Neither ſhall any perſon or perſons, by whom any Letters ſhall be ſent, or invita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions made on any others behalf, be elected for three years after: whereby colour ſhall be prevented.</p>
               <p n="6">6.
<note place="margin">Corporations elections.</note> Each Corporation who ſhall be at the charge, may after the ſame manner chuve particular Repreſentees, or may involve themſelves into the Sub-provincial elections, and there ſhare with their Neighbours: for each Repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee ſhall have quarterly paid him during his time of ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice for the Publique, twenty Marks: for none ſhall ſerve the Publique at his own charges, nor none ſhall have ſo much allowance, as meerly for ſalary to invite him to the work.</p>
               <p n="7">7.
<note place="margin">Number of Preſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives.</note> For each County ſhall be choſen four, and for <hi>York</hi> ſix as aforeſaid, which ſhall be the Repreſentees for the whole County or Province for which they ſhall be choſen; that is to ſay, for each reſpective Juriſdiction two: and each Sub-province ſhall elect two likewiſe, who ſhall ſerve by
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:119528:25"/>turns; that is to ſay, one the one half the year, and the other the other half: he that hath the pre-eminence in ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, to procede in ſervice; and where equal numbers ſhall be electors, the deciſion to be by lot.</p>
               <p n="9">9.
<note place="margin">None to be elected who ſhall have any ſuits in Law depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.</note> NO perſon who hath any Suit or Cauſe depending in Law ſhall be elected, nor be an Elector; for in all ſuch caſes, each acts his own Play: neither ſhall any member of Parliament for or during that year for which his ſervice is or ſhall be, receive any reward or compenſation for loſs, ſalary or ſervice, other then his ſalary which ſhall quarter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be allowed him as aforeſaid, to be paid by the reſpective Officer for the Liberty for which he ſhall ſerve.</p>
               <p n="10">10. That the Parliament ſhall have power to make and after Laws, to treat of and conclude Peace and War.</p>
               <p n="11">11.
<note place="margin">Committee for Petitions and Grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances to be diſpatched within a month.</note> That within one week after the ſitting of each re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective Parlaiemnt, a Committee ſhall be appointed, to receive all Petitions and Grievances, and to read and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider thereof; and ſuch as are fit to preſent to the houſe, to offer the ſame, ſo as anſwer may within one month be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven thereof; for it ill becomes a free State to ſhut the doors, eyes or ears of Juſtice, to any Suppliant: by which means ſome hundreds have periſhed of late years, whoſe bloud it may be feared is not yet pacified.</p>
               <p n="12">12.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>He that refuſes to ſerve in Parliament, to pay</hi> 20 li.</note> That none though elected ſhall be forced to ſerve in Parliament: but if any ſhall refuſe, he ſhall contribute 20 <hi>li.</hi> towards the charge of the next election, unleſs in caſe of ſickneſs or any bodily infirmity, in which caſe (none ſhall be compelled beyond his ſtrength) he is freely to be excuſed, and the next in order to ſupply his place: and where two or more ſhall be equally elected (that is to ſay) by equal numbers of electors, deciſion ſhall be made by lot, and not otherways.</p>
               <p n="13">13.
<note place="margin">None of the two laſt to be in any the nextſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding Parliament.</note> None ſhall be elected a member of any ſucceeding Parliament, who ſerved as member of either of the two laſt preceding Parliaments, the ſame rule annually to be obſerved; but that freedom of all the Nation be further
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:119528:26"/>admitted, and in all other Officers of inferiour rank in the whole Commonwealth, (the Regiſtries excepted, which are not to be altered, unleſs in caſe of corruption, neglect or abuſe of Truſt) ſo that it ſhall be free for each perſon, who ſhall carry himſelf worthy thereof, to be elected; neither ſhall any mans meanneſs of eſtate hinder his election, if his parts be ſuch as the Neighbourhood may confide therein: but all perſons whoſe eſtates are entrable in the Sub-provincial Regiſtry, are capable, if they be according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly qualified, of electing or being elected; for they are terms convertible; the elected is an elector, and the elector may be elected; each hath his ſingle voice by his paper in the box,
<note place="margin">Provincial Repreſentees to have double voices to the Sub-provincial. Repreſentees to ſerve on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for ſix months.</note> and no more.</p>
               <p n="14">14. Each Provincial Reproſentee convened in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhall have a double voice to each Sub-provincial; all voices to be given by balls, wherein each Provincial ſhall have two balls, and each Sub-provincial one ball: but in the Council of State they ſhall have equal voices.</p>
               <p n="15">15. The perſons elected ſhall ſerve by turns as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid; that is to ſay, one half for ſix months, and the other half for other ſix-months; and for each ſix months, one for each Provincial Riding, and one for each Sub-provincial Regiſtry ſhall meet at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> the firſt day of <hi>March</hi> annually, if it fall not on the Lords day; if ſo, the day fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing; and there entring the Houſe of Parliament, ſhall chuſe their Speaker, and take upon them the Government of the Nation for their time alotted; and at the end thereof, leave the ſame to their ſucceſſors, whereof ſixty to make a Houſe, and not under.</p>
               <p n="16">16.
<note place="margin">Council of State.</note> The firſt work they ſhall do after their meeting in <hi>March</hi> next, ſhall be to elect fourty perſons out of their whole number elected for that year, to be a Council of State; twenty whereof ſhall be out of the number of the perſons then convened, and twenty more out of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to convene in <hi>September</hi> followinge theſe fourty per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons for the firſt year ſo elected, to ſerve as members of the Council for a whole year, from the time of their reſpective
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:119528:26"/>conventions; and that twenty of the perſons which ſhall be continued in Council till the firſt of <hi>March</hi> next, ſhall continue there till the tenth of <hi>September</hi> next; the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers yearly to be choſen for the Council, to meet in Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil annually the tenth of <hi>March,</hi> and tenth of <hi>September,</hi> as their turns come: and all who ſhall be elected to ſerve in Council, ſhall there ſerve one whole year and no longer: whereby engroſſing of power and deſtroying of bodies ſhall be avoided. Any fifteen to be a Council, and not under.</p>
               <p n="17">17. Each member ſhall forfeit 2 <hi>li.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Forfeitures for not at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending in Parliament</note> which ſhall not meet in Parliament the firſt day whereon his ſervice is to commence; and for every day after which he ſhall be ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent (during the time of his appointed ſitting either in Parliament or Council) without licenſe, 20 <hi>s.</hi> unleſs in caſe of bodily diſtemper, or weakneſs not diſſembled, but real. The ſeveral forfeitures to be collected by the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeants at Arms attending the Houſe and Council for the time being, and accompted for and paid to the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardens of <hi>Margaret Weſtminſter,</hi> monthly, for relief of the poor in <hi>Westminster.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="18">18. The Affairs of the Army, Admiralty and Navy,
<note place="margin">Committee for the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally and Navy.</note> co be provided for by a Committee choſen by the Council, out of their own members, <hi>viz.</hi> out of each particular Conſular election ſix, their whole number to be twelve, whereof five to be a <hi>quorum,</hi> and not leſs, to be approved by Parliament; the Council, and alſo the ſaid Committee, to act in all things ſubordinate to the Parliament, and to obſerve their orders, and yearly to be changed as to the one half, every tenth of <hi>March</hi> twenty, and the other half each tenth of <hi>September</hi> twenty, to ſit for twelve months only year after year.</p>
               <p n="19">19. Six perſons ſhall be yearly elected by the Council,
<note place="margin">Publique Revenue.</note> &amp; approved by the Houſe of Parliament, for managing the receipts &amp; disburſements of all pubſike moneys, who ſhall twice every year paſs their Accompts, to a Committee to be choſen part out of the Houſe, and part out of the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:119528:27"/>
                  <hi>viz.</hi> at the end of ſix months after their commence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the laſt month of their reſpective ſervices.</p>
               <p n="20">20.
<note place="margin">Places of keeping Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtries and Courts.</note> Let the Provincial Regiſterial Courts be kept in the chief Town of every Privince, and each Sub-provinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Court and Regiſtry in ſome Market-Town within the ſame Hundred; and where no Market-town ſhall be in any Hundred, let a Market be appointed to be kept at ſome one Town conveniently ſeated, neer the middle of the ſame Hundred, and Authority given by Parliament for the ſame; and each Parochial Regiſtry in the ſame Town where the Pariſh Church, or publique meeting place of the ſame Pariſh is or ſhall be.</p>
               <p n="21">21.
<note place="margin">Honours to be conferred by Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> All perſons who ſhall have Eſtate entred in the National Regiſtry, to the clear yearly value of 10000 <hi>li. per annum,</hi> and ſhall pay Aſſeſments for ſo much to the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publique, ſhall be capable of the honour of Lordſhip, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred on him only by the Parliament; each perſon of 1000 <hi>li. per annum,</hi> of Knighthood; and each other perſon having 300 <hi>li. per annum,</hi> and upwards, be reputed an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſquire; and ſhall each of them give Coats of Arms, to be allowed by the King of Heralds for the time being. That no perſon who ſhall nor have 1000 <hi>li. per annum,</hi> ſhall be elected as a Provincial Repreſentee.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:119528:27"/>
               <head>The Fifth Days Work.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Its Publique aids muſt bear the charge,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Our Priviledges to enlarge.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Wherefore let Contributions be</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>In exigencies frank and free.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p n="1">1. LEt Aſſeſments be impoſed by Parliament yearly,
<note place="margin">Aſſeſments.</note> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the requiſition of the time, on each particular real and perſonal Eſtate,
<note place="margin">Aſſeſments to be impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> according to the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual values thereof, and Rents received; each paying for his ſtock in Husbandry or Trade, and each Uſurer for his Money lent at a certain rate, as rent of Land or intereſt of Money at the ſame rate, and ſtock in Trade or Husbandry at half the rate; the Land-Aſſeſs to be paid by the Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lord, and the Money-Aſſeſs by the Lender, to be defalked out of Rent or Intereſt, according to the proportions, by the Tenant or Borrower, who ſhall depoſite the ſame, as occaſion ſhall require, to the monthly Collectors thereof.</p>
               <p n="2">2.
<note place="margin">Great Aſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for the poor.</note> Let one great Aſſeſment be forthwith made for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of all the Poor in the Nation; and let a ſtock be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected in every Parochial Town, and a Trade ſet up for imploying and providing for all the poorer ſort of men, women and children: let a Maſter or Governour thereof, be appointed by the Regiſterial Court in every Pariſh, and ſuch a one as his Eſtate may be reſponſible for the ſtock with him intruſted, for which (together with the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits thereof, to be imployed according to the Rules to be given therefore) he ſhall give ſecurity; and this to be yearly taken care for, chiefly by the Church-wardens of each reſpective Pariſh. Let all charitable Contributions
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:119528:28"/>be imployed to the ſame purpoſe: Whereby if vigilancy and induſtry be uſed, a ſmall ſtock will in ſhort time in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe to a great inheritance, whereby the poor ſhall be equally provided for, to the beſt and richeſt in every Pariſh: ſo there ſhall be no crying out, nor complaining in our ſtreets.</p>
               <p n="3">3.
<note place="margin">Customs, Exciſe and Aſſeſments.</note> Let the Cuſtoms be annually regulated by the Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament at the time of changing of Repreſentees; only let the Repreſentees for the firſt ſix months, continue their ſittings ſo long after their time, together with the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentees for the latter ſix months, as to ſettle that, and the Exciſe and Aſſeſments for the next ſucceeding year; and to be done within twelve days. Let the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms be collected by ſuch Commiſſioners as have reſponſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Eſtates; and where any fraud or covin ſhall be diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, let care be taken therein for the prevention for the future.</p>
               <p n="4">4.
<note place="margin">Publique Collectors.</note> Let the Exciſe be collected by the Conſtables, and reſponded for to the Sheriff, as other Aſſeſments, and alſo all other Rents and Revenues payable to the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, for which no ſalary ſhall be allowed.</p>
               <p>In all Encloſures of Waſts,
<note place="margin">Encloſures of Waſts.</note> and Commons not ſtinted, one fourth part ſhall be alotted for proviſion for the Poor of the Pariſh where the ſame ſhall lie, to be committed to the care of the Maſter of the Work-houſe for the time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and by him imployed to the beſt advantage according to his truſts. One other fourth to the Lord for his Seg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niory, and half to the Commons: this rule in all caſes to be the ſame.</p>
               <p n="5">5.
<note place="margin">Encloſures of stinted Waſts and Towns-fields.</note> Where the Lords and Tenants, Owners and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prietors of two full third parts of the Incloſures, Field-Land and ſtinted Commons in any Mannor, Town or Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, ſhall agree to incloſe all or any part of the open Waſts or Common grounds of the ſame Town, no third party oppoſing ſhall hinder the ſame, ſo as proviſion be made for the poor to one half the alotment as aforeſaid; and the proportions alotted for the refuſers according to
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:119528:28"/>their ſeveral eſtates, quantity and quality to be conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: but if any ſhall endeavour to hinder a common good, he ſhall be ſeverely puniſhed therefore, either by the Judges in the next ſuperiour Court, or by the Juſtices of Peace at the next Quarter-Seſſions to be held for that Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, or by the Judges Itinerant in their Circuits.</p>
               <p n="6">6. In all proviſions for the Poor,
<note place="margin">Parochial proviſions for the poor.</note> each whole Pariſh to be one entire Corporation, and take care to diſpoſe of all Wanderers and Vagabonds, according to the directions of the Statutes in uſe, or elſe imploy them in work as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid.
<note place="margin">Publique Work-houſes</note> Let a large houſe be provided in each Pariſh-Town for a publike Work-houſe, where in ſome Manual occupa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion all the poor of the ſame Pariſh may be ſet on work, and provided for neceſſaries by the Maſter thereof, to be appointed as aforeſaid; to which purpoſe, let ſome Trade, whereof the Maſter of the Work-houſe to be a Freeman, be uſed in every Pariſh; and the children of all ſuch as ſhall not by their Parents be better provided for, to be imployed in the ſame after ſeven years old, as in all Towns where is conveniency of water for building Mills, and have Cole, let ſeveral ſorts of Smiths be, as for making of Knives, Swords, Scymiters; Guns, Sythes, Shears, Sciſſers; alſo for all manner of Work-tools and harneſs; and all ſuch who ſhall have uſe for wheels for grinding: alſo, Lock-ſmiths, Naylors and ſuch others, where no wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is, nor wheels ſhall not be requiſite; and where con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniency is, let Clothyers be: and to the end the Trade of Clothing may be the better managed, and with leſs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion, let thoſe Towns where much growth of Wool ſhall be, and want the conveniency of fire and water, be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed to the ſorting, breaking, mixing and ſpinning of Wool, in one Town for making of Jerſeys, Serges, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Stuffs of the like nature, in other Towns in ſpinning Wool for making cloath according to the ſeveral ſorts thereof, the fineſt by its ſelf, and the courſeſt by its ſelf, and the middle ſort by it ſelf; and a certain rate allowed to each perſon for the work they ſhall do, not exceeding
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:119528:29"/>four parts of five of the real value of the work; one fifth being ſtill to be allowed to the common ſtock.</p>
               <p n="7">7.
<note place="margin">Husband-men to have the help of labourers in the common Work-houſe.</note> That in all caſes where any perſons imployed at work upon the common ſtock, ſhall be deſired to aſſiſt the Husband-man, at any out-work in the Fields, there ſhall a fourth part of the wages be imployed to the common ſtock; which wages ſhall be paid to the Maſter of the Work-houſe, who ſhall have the command of all under the age of twenty one as Apprentices, and all above as Journey-men; without whoſe licenſe none ſhall go to work abroad: which ſhall not be denied in Seed-time, Hay-time or Harveſt, upon reaſonable rates.</p>
               <p n="8">8.
<note place="margin">Trades to be erected in Flax and Hemp.</note> In thoſe Towns where ſhall be ſtore of Hemp or Flax, let ſome Towns be imployed in dreſſing and fitting the ſame for ſpinning, according to the ſeveral ſorts thereof; another in ſpinning fine Linen, another the middle, and another the courſer ſort, and another weaving the ſame; others alſo in making Cordage and Ropes.</p>
               <p n="9">9.
<note place="margin">In Wood.</note> In Towns where wood ſhall be plentiful, let one be imployed by Coopers, another by Carpenters, another by Tanners, another by makers of Waines, Waggons, Carts, Plows, Sledges, &amp; other Utenſils for Husbandry; &amp; in every Parochial-Town let there be in the common Work-houſe, a Smith, a Shooe-maker and a Taylor, with their ſeveral ſervants ſubſervient to the publique Maſter: and in thoſe Towns which ſhall be imployed in making of wire Pins, Needles or Bonelace, the Maſter of the work ſhall once a week pay off all the Workers of the ſame Trade, and ſhall furniſh them with ſtuff for making thereof; and when they are made, ſell them for the advantage of the common ſtock: and ſo in all other Trades.</p>
               <p n="10">10.
<note place="margin">Proviſton in the common Work-houſes</note> In the common Work-houſes proviſion ſhall be made for all perſons of all ages, ſexes and conditions, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther young or old, which are not able to help themſelves, and be therein imployed in ſuch works as their ſtrengths, genius's and abilities are fitteſt to manage and undergo; &amp; let the females be imployed in ſeveral works by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:119528:29"/>and have Miſtreſſes for their Tutreſſes and Gardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans; where they may be imployed in ſpinning, carding, ſowing, weaving lace, ribband, tape, and other things; in ſetting of Cuſhions, Carpets, Hangings, and other things fit for the work of women.</p>
               <p>By which means the poor of the Nation ſhall not only be provided for, but the Nation ſhall be thereby enriched; and for every penyworth of ſtuff that the Nation now affords of vendible Commodity in other Countries, it ſhall in few years afford three, four, five or ſix times the quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; which ſhall much enrich the Merchants thereof alſo.</p>
               <p n="11">11.
<note place="margin">Juſtices e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected.</note> Let the Repreſentees annually choſen for members in Parliament, be the Juſtices of Peace for the ſame year; and thoſe which ſhall be reſident in the Country to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergo that ſervice, and in all things obſerve the directions of Parliament, for levying of Souldiers, regulating of Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſments, and all other things whatſoever.</p>
               <p n="12">12. Every perſon or perſons,
<note place="margin">Planting.</note> who ſhall at any time make any new Encloſures upon any Waſts, Commons, Town-fields or commonable grounds, ſhall within every Pole ſet or plant at leaſt one plant or ſet of Aſh, Ok, Elm or Beech, and preſerve the ſame for growth; and in thoſe Countries where fruit-trees will grow and bear fruit, the like may be enjoyned alſo, upon forfeiture of 2 <hi>s.</hi> for eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry defect, to be collected by the Conſtable by warrant from the Regiſter, upon information to be made thereof to the Court by the Church-wardens, or any one or more of them in any Pariſh for the time being: which forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures the one half to be imployed to the common ſtock of the ſame Town, the other half to the Informer or Informers.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:119528:30"/>
               <head>The Sixth Days Work.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>It's mutual Commerce that brings</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Beggers unto the ſtate of Kings.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Trade.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And if we view the fruits of Trade,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>It is a tree of pleaſant ſhade.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p n="1">1.
<note place="margin">Cuſtoms.</note> LEt certain Taxes, Cuſtoms and Impoſitions, be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed upon all Manufactures which the Merchant ſhall bring from other Countries: but let all the Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factures of this Nation be ſold and exported free from the ſame for ſeven years, whereby the Country may be encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged to Trade.</p>
               <p n="2">2.
<note place="margin">Corporations of Trades.</note> Let all the Trades-men in every Riding or diſtinct half Provincial Liberty, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> well of the common Work-houſes as others of every diſtinct Trade, be a particular Society and Corporation, and have power to elect Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers and make Laws amongſt themſelves, for the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage and benefit of the whole; and alſo authority to put thoſe Laws in execution, and to meet once a Month at a place certain within each diviſion, or to appoint any other time or place within their limits (whereof publique notice ſhall be given at the laſt precedent meeting) for the doing of any thing requiſite for the benefit and advantage of the ſame Trade.</p>
               <p n="3">3.
<note place="margin">Youth to be brought up in Trades.</note> That all perſons within the Commonwealth of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> ſhall bring up their ſons to ſome Trade or other, after the age of fourteen till the age of twenty one at leaſt; un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der which notion, the Husband-man is reputed a Trades-man, which Trade none ſhall follow who with his own Team ſhall not Till every year twenty Acres of Land or upwards, as a Maſter-Husbandman.</p>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:119528:30"/>
               <p n="4">4. Every Parochial Town ſhall have a School-maſter,
<note place="margin">Parochial Schools and Writing-maſter.</note> who ſhall teach all children in the ſame Pariſh, to write and read Engliſh, and caſt Accompts, from the age of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven till the age of fourteen, at which age they ſhall be ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther imployed in their Trades, or ſent to other Schools; and all children brought up in the common Work-houſe ſhall ſpend two houres every day in the ſame School, one in the forenoon and one in the after; and at ten years old and after, the afternoons hours ſhall be ſpent in writing and caſting accompts, for which every School-maſter where no proviſion is already made, ſhall have 10 <hi>li. per annum</hi> quarterly paid by the Conſtable for the time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, beſides the gratuities of the richer ſort of people.</p>
               <p n="5">5.
<note place="margin">Sub-provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial grand School.</note> In every Sub-provincial or Market-Town ſhall be a free Grammar-School erected, where ſhall be a Maſter who ſhall have allowance of 40 <hi>li.</hi> and an Uſher of 20 <hi>li. per annum,</hi> paid quarterly by the Sheriffs ſubſtitute for the time being; whither all the youths of that ſub-Province (whom their Parents or Friends ſhall intend for Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars) ſhall be ſent at the age of ten, and there continue till they ſhall be reſpectively fit for the Univerſity; whither none ſhall be admitted under the age of ſixteen.</p>
               <p>In every Sub-provincial Market-town,
<note place="margin">Scrivener.</note> ſhall be a Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vener or writing Maſter, who ſhall teach to write and caſt accompts; with whom every Scholar in the Grammar-School ſhall ſpend at leaſt one half day every week, or one hour a day for three days in the week: which ſaid Maſter ſhall have the yearly allowance of 10 <hi>li.</hi> paid by the parties aforeſaid, beſides gratuities.</p>
               <p n="6">6. There ſhall alſo be a Muſick-maſter,
<note place="margin">Muſick Master.</note> who ſhall have the yearly allowance of 10 <hi>li.</hi> beſides gratuities, with whom every Scholar ſhall ſpend one half day every week, or an hour a day for three days in the week.</p>
               <p n="7">7.
<note place="margin">Time of ſtay at the grand School.</note> All ſuch as ſhall be ſent to the Grammar-School at ten, ſhall be continued there till fourteen; whereby the youth of the Country ſhall be fitted (by that time (they ſhall attain twenty one) for the ſervice of Princes; and all
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:119528:31"/>who ſhall be imployed in Trades, ſhall be able to live thereon, and be helpful to their friends.</p>
               <p n="8">8.
<note place="margin">Army and Militia.</note> The preſent Armies now in being, to be diſpoſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Militia's of the ſeveral Counties and Provinces of the Nation, each Commander to have the conveniency of reſiding in his own Country, or the next adjacent; and let the Souldiers retire to the commands in their own Countries, and to have half pay for the time of their reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences there, and to Muſter once a month, and be in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſs on all occaſions, when the Parliament ſhall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand; and ſo many as ſhall be commanded to the Guard, either to this Town, or elſewhere, for all the time of their ſervice, to have pay according to the preſent eſtabliſhment: and let the Militia be compleated together with the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Army, to the antient number of the Trained-bands.</p>
               <p n="9">9.
<note place="margin">Diſaffected diſarmed.</note> Let all diſaffected perſons be diſarmed, and their Arms kept and ſecured, in the hands of the ſeveral Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders of the Militia, to be diſpoſed of from time to time as the Parliament ſhall appoint: and let no Officer of the Army or Militia be elected for a Member of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; or if any ſuch be, that during his attendance in Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament his Command ſhall be transferred to another, who ſhall perſonally attend the ſame, as well when they ſhall be upon ſervice, as when reſident in the Countries: to the end no diſorder appear, but the ſame may be timely pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented.</p>
               <p n="10">10.
<note place="margin">Univerſities purged.</note> Let the ſeveral Univerſities of this Nation be purg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from all dregs and reliques of Popiſh ſuperſtition; and let all Oathes formerly taken by any graduates there, be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boliſhed; and in lieu thereof, let the ſame Oath that the Judges and Juſtices are to take, be adminiſtred by per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons thereto Authorized; and ſuch as ſhall refuſe the ſame, be removed: and let all graduates upon their admiſſion into order from time to time, take the ſame Oath, and no other; and let all Rights and Priviledges as to their Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Rights, be ſecured; and ſuch orders inſtituted, as may beſt prepare the youth thither ſent, for the ſervice of God
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:119528:31"/>and their Country: to which end, let the heads of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Colledges meet and conſider of ſuch propoſitions by a joynt conſent, as may be fit for the Parliament to ratifie and eſtabliſh, as well for the ſtudy of Divinity, as Phyſick, Aſtronomy, or other Arts there fit to be read and ſtudied.</p>
               <p n="11">11.
<note place="margin">Graduates</note> Let none take any degree in any Univerſity before the full age of twenty one, nor any be admitted publique<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to Preach before the age of twenty ſix years at the leaſt.</p>
               <p n="12">12.
<note place="margin">Cathedrals.</note> Let in every Province the Cathedral or chief Church in the ſame Province be repaired and endowed with 400 <hi>li. per annum,</hi> at the leaſt; whereof 300 <hi>li.</hi> to be to two Miniſters to officiate there, and the other 100 <hi>li.</hi> for the under-Officers in the ſame Church, <hi>viz.</hi> 50 <hi>li.</hi> to an Aſſiſtant, and 50. more to the Clerk, Sextons, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="13">13.
<note place="margin">Sub-pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincial Churches, and Paro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chial.</note> Let the Sub-provincial Church in each Market<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>town have allowance of 200 <hi>li. per annum,</hi> for two Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters conſtantly to attend the ſervice of God there; and let each Parochial Miniſter have at leaſt 60 <hi>li. per annum:</hi> and where any Parochial Miniſter by Tythes or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways ſhall have above 150 <hi>li. per annum,</hi> let the ſurpluſage go to the augmentation of his next Neighbour incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bants, to make each of them the annual value of 60 <hi>li.</hi> or upwards; but no augmentation to be granted to any Church which ſhall have 100 <hi>li. per annum,</hi> in preſent be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, for the Miniſtry there.</p>
               <p n="14">14. Let no quarrellers,
<note place="margin">Perſons to be beneficed.</note> railers or State-Incendiaries be admitted to any Benefice; but let ſuch be appointed, as in ſobriety &amp; meekneſs be have themſelves, teaching the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel of Chriſt as the ſame is delivered in the holy Bible, without nice Inventions to intangle the hearers of the word; &amp; let every Province be a Claſſis, &amp; conſtitute Orders and Decrees for the well governing of the ſeveral people of that Province: but none to be put in execution, till the ſame ſhall be confirmed by Authority of Parliament.</p>
               <p n="15">15. Let the Lords day be carefully obſerved;
<note place="margin">Lords day obſerved.</note> and if any ſhall diſturb any publique Miniſter, whether in his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rochial Miniſtry, or elſewhere in his exerciſe of the day, let
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:119528:32"/>a fine of 10 <hi>s.</hi> be impoſed, and collected from every offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; the offenders of what rank ſoever to be impriſoned in the common Stocks of the Town till the fine ſhall be paid, by any Parochial Officers or other perſon or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons whatſoever, at the command of the Miniſter who ſhall be diſturbed, whether he be beneficed or no.</p>
               <p n="16">16.
<note place="margin">Seditious perſons pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed.</note> That all ſeditious and ſcandalous perſons, who ſhall pretend as Miniſters to teach the people, and ſhall ſow or foment any ſeditious, ſcandalous or blaſphemous opinions to the diſquiet of the people, ſhall be taken and imployed in the common Work-houſe, where he ſhall be ſo found, in ſuch manual occupation as his body may bear; and to have only two parts of his gettings for his allowance; and not to depart thence till by the Magiſtracy of the ſame place he ſhall be releaſed, which ſhall not be of one full week for the firſt offence, one month for the ſecond, and a quarter of a year for the third.</p>
               <p n="17">17. Let publique Banks be erected, and Fiſhing in our own Seas not neglected; which with Cuſtoms ſhall defray the Maritime charge. But this is ſuppoſed muſt be the work of another Repreſentative; for the Publique credit is at too low an ebb to expect it now at preſent.</p>
               <p>Now the Lord proſper the work in the hands of the Magiſtracy for the good of the Nation in general, and themſelves and their poſterities in particular, who ſhall doubtleſs be the greateſt ſharers of the fruit of their own labours, be they good or bad.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>When Work is done in ſeaſon fit,</l>
                  <l>The God of grace will proſper it.</l>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix">
               <pb facs="tcp:119528:32"/>
               <head>APPENDIX.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>LEt none miſtake the Authors purpoſe in the precedent diſcourſe to be, that every word and ſentence ſhould paſs for a Law: No, if ſo, it had not ſeen light in ſo careleſs a dreſs, as it is. But conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering the preſent condition we are in, the Juncture of affairs we are under, and the opportunity is now in our hands, the Author hath ſent abroad-this Model of a ſettlement, as a rough draught, to be viewed cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected, amended, and (ſo far as our Governours ſhall ſee meet) made uſe of: which if they will, may in leſs then ſeventy days be perfected; thereby ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the facility of doing, what is by all men ſo much deſired; Wherein, as is ſaid before, there's nothing new or ſtrange: for the chief</hi> (viz <hi>the Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterial) part thereof is as antient as any inheritance we have, as well wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes the Inrolm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nts in Chancery, and Court-rolls of the ſeveral Copie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold Mannors, which are no other thing ſave Registries ill kept; and yet as they are, there's more ſafety, and leſs trouble in ſetling Eſtates there, then in other caſes. And if our Anceſtors ſo long ago were ſo wiſe and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident, it may be no ill courſe for us to imitate them in what's good; and where they were defective, to furniſh ſupplies requiſite. Beſides, it affords more Conveniency and regularity in elections, and more certainty of electing the beſt and ſitteſt men for Governours, then any other way yet propounded to publique view hath done. Whereupon the great wheel of Government is as eaſily convertible, and with as much ſecurity as may be imagined, or can be deſired; wherein all intereſts wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> finde ſecurity and profit: And to the Publique (above the charges of carrying it on) will ariſe a conſiderable Revenue. Now that a ſettlement is requiſite, our preſent Governours in their Declaration of the</hi> 7. <hi>of</hi> May, <hi>have not only acknowledged, but pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed, as men and as Chriſtians vigorouſly to endeavour. The Army in their humble Petition and Addreſs of the </hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>2. <hi>of</hi> May, <hi>did unanimouſly repreſent to them, as in the</hi> 1, 7, 9, 11, <hi>and</hi> 13. <hi>Articles is very very apparent, and in the cloſe thereof, do beg the bleſſing and preſence of the Lord with them in the proſecution and bringing ſorth thereof. Many well affected in ſundry Counties of</hi> England <hi>have already Petitioned for it: The eyes of all the Nation are upon our Governours expecting it; our inteſtine diviſions ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe it; the conſederacies of</hi> Europe <hi>require it, and our own ſafety com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands it, to be ſpeedily undertaken, and vigorouſly proſecuted: which if pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate intereſts belaid aſide (by the doers) will be eaſily perfected; And the more durable it ſhall be, the more honour it ſhall be to the doers, whoſe honours ſhall grow with the Government they ſhall eſtabliſh, and whilſt the ſame endures they ſhall continue to all poſterity. But ſome ſuſpect the words (conſtant to this Commonwealth) in the oath appointed to be taken by the Judges, Juſtices and other Officers and Miniſters, intend no other ſettle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to be expected, then what we now are under: which if ſo, ſad doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs will be the effects: for clearing of which ſuſpition (which if fomented may be cauſe of contraction of ill humors) a ſpeedy manifeſtation of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, by actions rather then words, may be wiſhed, and is by many deſired.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Some other things the Author intended to have ſpoke of; as the Spaniards
<pb facs="tcp:119528:33"/>preſent growth, who by ſubjection of</hi> Portugal, <hi>Alliance with</hi> France, <hi>confederacy with the Emperour, the</hi> Pole, <hi>the</hi> Dane, <hi>and the rest of the</hi> German <hi>Princes, (in whoſe quarrel our brethren the</hi> Dutch <hi>are endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to be engaged) his late acquiſition of Treaſure from the Weſt, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the ſpecious pretence of re-enthroning again the</hi> Stuarts, <hi>(which title if once ſet on ſoot, what Partizans it will find amongſt us, is worth conſideration) by all which we may be invited to a ſpeedy care and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour ſo to ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tile our ſelves at home, and provide for alliance abroad (e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially with our brethren the</hi> Dutch, <hi>whereby our Fleets may be recalled from their expenſive attendances on other Princes occaſions, to more profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble imployments for their reſpective Countries, for both whoſe Trades the Seas and the World is wide enough) whereof we are now deftitute and naked,
<note place="margin">A general contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bution from the poorer ſort will be dangerous, and the rich have moſt reaſon to give, thereby to ſecure their Eſtates from dangers of inſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections to be made by diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented parties.</note> as may encourage our Country-men to contribute preſent ſupplies of money for the doing of all that ſhall be requiſite: to which purpoſe it would be no difficulty to ſuch as have plentiful Eſtates, full Stocks, and Money in their Purſes, to give a years Rent of all their Revenues; nay to enjoy an unbiaſſed ſettlement, none ſuch would deny it, or repine thereat (thereby to ſecure the reſt) though upon ſuch ſlippery foundations as we now ſtand, few or none will be free to contribute any thing at all; As alſo of the ſeveral diviſions, rents and ſchiſms in the Church, whereby that intereſt of</hi> Spain <hi>is no little advanced, Our fifth Monarchiſts ignorantly endeavouring to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduce the Inquiſition, as a Scourge to their own backs; And of the ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>endedneſs, covetouſneſs; and other eminent ſigns of Antichriſtianity, predo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minant in and amongſt many Congregational ſocieties, which of their own particular purſes provide maintenance from their own Miniſters, little or nothing differing in Doctrine from the Parochial Miniſtry, though they claſh in words as if they would ſet on fire the whole frame of Nature, each judging and condemning all that are not of their own opinions: which from what root the ſame ſprings, or to what end they aim, the Author is not quick enough ſighted to diſcern, though he hath obſerved many ſuch to clime to places of profit more then other men: Things ill becoming Saints, if we believe Chriſt, who ſaith, His Kingdom is not of this world; and called his Apoſtles from their worldly callings, to be Preachers of the Goſpel: ſo that the Author ſees not why the Magiſtrate may not,
<note place="margin">Query how con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent it is to the Weale Publique to permit any fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dators to any un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known intereſts, and what the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequents thereof may be, ſith all have liberty to preach the Word of God in publike, and lead their lives according thereto without reſtraint.</note> nay ought not, to bring all ſuch to civil obedience and conformity, according to the Rule of Chriſt, who commanded his Apoſtles to take what ſhould be ſet before them; which may import, that the Miniſters of the Goſpel may freely participate of ſuch allowance as the Magiſtrate ſhall alot for their maintenance (whether by Tythes or otherways) without asking any queſtion for Conſcience ſake: and is more properly their duty ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> to do, then (Pope or Antichriſt like) to make themſelves every one head and Lord over the flock he ſuperintends, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by dividing the Church into Factions; which how dangerous it is, the whole current of Scriptures declare. But the length of this Diſcourſe exceeding its purpoſed limits, the Author commends the Premiſes to the conſideration of our preſent Governours, and all others in the Nation which wiſh well to our Engliſh Sion, And them to the good and gracious direction and prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the Almighty, in hopes of an happy iſſue, which God grant, Amen,</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
